The Central Research Institute's 1st January knowledge lecture will begin.
The Central Research Institute's 1st January knowledge lecture will begin.
Let's welcome Director Peng Xun-ning, the vice president, to join us.
Let's welcome Director Peng Xun-ning, the vice president, to join us.
Good evening, everyone.
Good evening, everyone.
I am very happy to welcome the special professor of the Taiwan National University, Dr. Li Bingshan.
I am very happy to welcome the special professor of the Taiwan National University, Dr. Li Bingshan.
Thank you.
Thank you.
He is also a member of the Academia Sinica
他也是中研院的不叫做老人年輕人
Around 1991 to 1997
大概1991年到1997年
He used to be the director of our information office
曾經是我們資訊所的所長
And now go back to National Taiwan University
然後現在又再回台大
Today he... I send it back to my mother's house
今天他又...我下發去回娘家
He's also happy to be back at his mother's house
他也很高興能夠回到娘家
Today is of course offering a very new woman
今天當然是提供很新的女人
look at so many people
看看那麼多人滿座
I know there are seats in front
就知道前面還有座位
There are still seats in front of you. You're welcome.
前面還有座位不要客氣
ok my...
好 我的...
Just give a brief introduction to Professor Li Linshan
就對李林山教授做一個簡單的介紹
Although everyone has
雖然大家的手上都有
Professor Li Linshan
李林山教授
Graduated from the Department of Electrical Engineering, National Taiwan University
畢業於台大電機系
Later to Stanford University in the United States
後來到美國 Stanford大學
get a Ph.D.
拿到博士
1979 very early
1979年很早
started teaching at National Taiwan University
就開始在台大任教
He used to be the Director of Qi in the Information Department of National Taiwan University
曾經任臺大資訊系的氣主任
As I just said, the director of the Institute of Information, Academia Sinica
剛才講過 中央研究院資訊所所長
Chairman of National Taiwan University Research and Development Association
臺大研發會的主任委員
Dean of School of Electronics, National Taiwan University
臺大電子學院的院長
Dr. Doge and his work in the United States
他在美國的公督博士及工作的
area of ​​expertise at the time was
時的專業領域是
satellite communication
衛星通訊
When returning to China in 1979
1979年回國的時候
Research resources at that time
那個時候的研究資源
still lacking
還很匱乏
Then he decided to find a
那他決定找一個
with minimum cost
用最少經費
most common equipment
最普通的設備
possible research directions
就可以做的研究方向
and start by reading a textbook
並由讀一本教科書開始
Try doing voice technology research
嘗試做語音技術的研究
first in 1984
首先在1984年
developed
發展出
Chinese Speech Synthesis Technology
華語語音合成的技術
And completed the first edition of Great Wisdom in 1991
並在1991年完成第一版的大智慧
Chinese Speech Recognition Technology
華語語音的辨識技術
Let the Chinese computer can speak
讓中文電腦可以說
Chinese Listening to Chinese
華語聽華語
he in 1992
他在1992年
For Chinese computer
以對中文電腦的
Contributions to input technology
以於輸入技術的貢獻
Elected as IEEE Fellow
獲得當選叫做IEEE Fellow
It is the fourth IEEE Fellow in Taiwan
就是台灣第四位的IEEE Fellow
I still remember 1994
我還記得1994年
When Dean Li returned to Taiwan
李院長回台灣的時候
I will accompany Dean Li to the information center
我陪著李院長去資訊所看看
As a result, Director Li Linshan showed off his Spirit No. 1
結果李林山所長展示他的精神一號
With his self-certified gun yuan's recitative input voice
用他的自證槍元的朗誦式的輸入語音
Then display the voice in the computer
然後顯示出電腦裡頭的語音
At that time the input was
那時候輸入是
Because his self-certification gun element is recitative
因為他的自證槍元是朗誦式的
So it works great
所以有很好的效果
I'm still very impressed
我印象還非常的深刻
Then he also said that the computer can focus
然後他還說電腦是可以焦的
After a person with an accent like me gets burnt
像我這種有口音的焦了以後
He can recognize my accent
他就可以認得我的口音
very impressed
很有深刻的印象
Then in 2010 with Chinese voice technology
然後在2010年再以對中文語音技術
and contributions to voice information search technology
以及語音資訊搜尋技術的貢獻
Elected ISDA Fellow of the International Phonetic Association
當選國際語音學會的ISDA Fellow
At that time, there were only about 30 ISDA Fellows in the world
當時全球的ISDA Fellow只有30個人左右
including many linguists
包括很多語言學家
those three asians
那三位亞洲人
he is one of three asians
他是三位亞洲人之一
Of course in Taiwan in 1993
當然在台灣1993年
Academic Award from the Ministry of Education
就獲得教育部的學術獎
Received a National Award from the Ministry of Education in 2004
2004年獲得教育部的國家獎座
So I'm very focused on doing research all the way.
所以一路非常專心做研究
Also did a lot of academic administrative services
也做了很多學術行政的服務
shall we applaud
我們是不是以熱烈的掌聲
Welcome to Li Pingshan Newspaper Office
歡迎李平山 報社
Do you hear my voice? Hear it
各位听到我的声音吗?听到
OK, thank you Vice President Peng
好,谢谢彭副院长
Then I am very glad to have this opportunity to come back to Academia Sinica
那么很高兴有这个机会回到中研院来
As he said, it's like going back to her mother's house
如他所说的好像是回娘家一样
then i remember when i was here
那时我想起我在这里的时候
There was a beautiful time more than ten years ago
十多年前曾经有过一段美丽的时光
Then every plant and tree in Academia Sinica, bit by bit
那么中研院的一草一木,一点一滴
Lili is still in my heart, Xu Xurusheng
在我的心里仍然是丽丽在目,许许如生
I think Academia Sinica can be regarded as eternal
我觉得中研院可以算是万古不变
On the one hand, it is also a day and a month
一方面也是日行月行
it's nice to be back here
那很高兴回到这儿来
Thank you all for coming to today's speech
也谢谢大家都来听今天的演讲
Ok, so it's the first time I've seen such an advanced pointer
好,那么我是第一次看到这么先进的pointer
ok so let me try to use it
可以,所以让我试试看用它
I think it might be better if I use this so I don't have to face the computer
我觉得如果我用这个我可以不用对着电脑,可能比较好
No, I haven't used it, so let me try using
不,我没用过,所以让我试着用
Everyone can take a look
大家可以看看
today's speech topic
今天的演講題
I know everyone
我各位知道
This sesame open the door
這個芝麻開門
but you also
但是各位也
sorry i just can't use it
抱歉 我就是不會用
but you know me
但是各位了解我這個
not talking about the Arabian Nights
不是在講天方夜談
Not talking about Alibaba
也不是在講阿里巴巴
I'm talking about the gates to treasures of knowledge
我講的是知識寶藏的大門
OK I'm talking about the door to the treasure trove of knowledge
OK 我講的是知識寶藏的大門
So today's speech is mainly
那麼今天的演講主要是
these parts
這幾個部分
then i will start by explaining
那麼我會先說明
Speech signal and its analysis
語音訊號以及它的分析
and then i will
然後呢 我會
this
這個
Explain how speech recognition works
解釋一下語音辨識是如何做到的
Then enter today's topic
然後進入今天的主題
is the search for audio information
就是語音資訊的搜尋
and finally
然後最後呢
before the end
在結束之前
i will start by saying
我會先說一下
and finally
然後最後呢
before the end
在結束之前
I'll show you a few live demonstrations
會給各位看幾個現場的展示
Then I will divide this general knowledge
那我會分這個一般性的知識
professional knowledge
專業性的知識
and the three levels of language learning
以及語言學習的三個層次
come to show everyone
來給大家看
everybody look
各位看
I feel like this one moves more than I thought
我覺得好像這個動得比我想像的多
Then maybe I'll use this
那也許我還是用這個吧
This step back a bit, I still use
這個退步一點我還是用
I'd better use this
我還是用這個好了
get used to it
比較習慣一點
ok then let's start
好 那我們先開始說
Everyone knows what I'm talking about today
各位知道我今天講的事情
then we understand that the network
那麼我們了解這個網路
It is already our daily life today
已經是我們今天日常生活
an indispensable part
不可或缺的重要的部分
All kinds of things are online
各種各樣東西都在網路上
Then it's especially worth talking about
那麼尤其值得一談的
It should mean that we all understand
應該是說我們都了解
像Google, Amazon, Facebook, YouTube
像Google, Amazon, Facebook, YouTube
These things provide our daily life
這些東西提供了我們日常生活
a lot of information
非常多的資訊
The other thing we can say is
那另外一點我們可以說的是
Knowledge Warranty as we know it in the past
過去我們所熟知的知識保固
Like a library or a museum, etc.
像是圖書館或者博物館等等
It has been gradually virtualized or demonstrated
已經慢慢的都虛擬化或者示威化
We are doing research today and looking for a paper
我們今天做研究要找一篇論文
Few people have to go to the library to find
已經很少人要跑去圖書館找了
Because we found it on the Internet
因為我們就在網路上找了
Similarly, online courses, distance learning, e-books, these
同樣網路課程遠距教學電子書這些
It has also become the most efficient learning tool.
也都已經變成最有效率的學習工具了
in this situation
在這個情形之下
We can understand the only commonality of human beings today
我們可以了解今天人類唯一的共同
Is Safeguarding Where Online?
是保障在哪裡 在網路上
if you think so
如果這樣想的話
All knowledge becomes digital content
所有的知識都變成數位內容了
What is the most attractive form of digital content at this time?
這個時候最吸引人的數位內容形態是什麼呢
We immediately thought of audio-visual multimedia
我們馬上想到就是影音多媒體
The reason we will understand immediately
這個原因我們馬上了解
Because of multimedia it can be colorful
因為多媒體它可以有聲有色
can be colorful
可以多彩多姿
Then its biggest feature is that it can be written without text
那麼它的最大特點是它可以不帶文字的
But it can have voice narration
不過它可以帶語音旁白
The speech we speak is the sound signal of human language
我們講的語音就是人的語言的聲音的訊號
then our voice
那麼我們說話的聲音
From this point of view
從這個觀念來想的話
we will understand
我們就了解
Multimedia as long as it comes with voice narration
多媒體只要它帶著語音旁白
Usually it can describe digital content
通常它就可以說明數位內容
theme concept
主題概念
For example
舉例來講
when i listen to tv news
我聽電視新聞的時候
i can close my eyes
我可以閉著眼睛
just listen to him
光是聽他講的
I already know the news he's talking about
我已經知道他講的新聞了
I don't need to actually watch his picture
我不太需要真的看他的畫面
Of course you can watch
當然看也可以了
but i can ignore it
但是我可以不看
This means
這個意思說明
The voice has been very clearly described
語音已經非常清楚的描述
his multimedia content
他的多媒體的內容
so I can use it for digital content searches
因此我可以用他來做數位內容的搜尋
On the other hand we also understand
那另一方面我們也瞭解
Today's Web Searches
今天的網路搜尋
still text-based
仍然是以文字為基礎
Just like you enter a text when surfing the Internet
就像你上網都是輸入一個文字
He is doing text comparison
他在做文字的比對
So even if you're looking for a YouTube video
因此即使你找的是YouTube裡面的視訊
we will find him
我們會找到他
Also because of whoever uploaded that video
也是因為上傳那段視訊的人
while he is uploading
他在上傳的同時
he wrote a bunch of words
他寫了一堆文字
Then we were looking for him based on text
然後我們是根據文字在找他的
This shows that today this part still has a very large space
這個說明今天這部分仍然有非常大的空間
not yet developed
尚未發展
Because on the one hand we also understand smartphones and devices
因為一方面我們也瞭解智慧型手機以及器
Other possible Internet tools
其他可能的上網工具
what's there
有些什麼呢
we'll find out
我們馬上了解
For example, there can be various electronic devices in the car
譬如說車上可以有各種的電子裝置
At home, such as the living room and kitchen
在家裡譬如說客廳廚房
Can have various home appliances
可以有各種家電
There are also various accessories
還有各種隨身配備的
e.g. glasses, watches
譬如說眼鏡 手錶
These may become the tools we use to surf the Internet
這些都可能成為我們上網的工具
Common features of these things
這些東西的共同特點
yes they can let us anytime, anywhere
是他們可以讓我們隨時隨地
Connect with global knowledge and information
跟全球的知識及資訊相連
They also have a great feature
他們還有一個大的特點
It's thin, short, and ubiquitous
就是輕薄短小無所不在
can enter our daily life
可以進入我們日常生活
use anytime, anywhere
隨時隨地使用
i.e. personal computer
也就是說個人電腦
are no longer everyday information users
已經不再是日常資訊使用者
the only darling
唯一的寵兒
And this we found
而這個我們發現
under this environment
在這個環境之下
What is the most convenient interface for surfing the Internet?
最方便的上網的界面是什麼呢
at least voice is one of them
至少語音是其中之一
Why voice is one of them
為什麼說語音是其中之一呢
at least the first
至少第一個
because it's just us talking
因為它只是我們說話而已
we can talk anytime anywhere
我們隨時隨地都能說話
So you can use it anytime, anywhere
所以隨時隨地都能用
Any of these tools we can talk to him
這些工具任何一個我們都可以跟他說話
So any tool can be used
所以任何工具都可以用
Talking is the most convenient and natural
說話又是最方便自然的
Another point is that the voice is the most special
還有一點這是語音最特別
that is, it can be said in place
就是它可以一句到位
what is a sentence in place
什麼叫一句到位
Let's say I'm looking for the US presidential election
假設說我要找美國總統大選
I'd say the US presidential election is already in place
我就說美國總統大選就已經到位了
Any touch other than voice
語音其他的任何觸控啊
It is impossible to press a button in one sentence
使按鍵都不可能一句到位
So Voice Has Its Benefits
所以語音有它的好處
So you can imagine
那麼因此各位可以想像
what am i talking about here
我這邊要講的是什麼呢
This is our future online world
這是我們未來的網路世界
or today's online world
或者今天的網路世界
in our digital content
我們的數位內容裡面
or knowledge
或者知識裡面
there are a bunch of text
有一堆是文字的
There are a bunch of multimedia
有一堆是多媒體的
this will be more and more
這個會越來越多
then we can still search with today's text
那麼我們仍然可以用今天的文字搜尋
go find these things
去找這些東西
as long as it has words written on it
只要它上面都寫了字
But we can also search directly by voice
但是我們也可以直接用語音的搜尋
At this time, I can directly use
這個時候我可以直接用
this smart phone
這個智慧型的手機
or similar handheld interface
或者類似的手持界面
Then I go directly to voice with voice
然後我直接用語音去找語音
I can find his things based on the content of his voice
我可以根据他的语音内容去找他的东西
If I find the text
我如果找到是文字
I can also use listening to ask him to synthesize it for me, etc.
我也可以用听的叫他合成给我听等等
that's what we're going to talk about today
这就是我们今天要说的事情
In other words, although today's Internet interface is this
也就是说虽然今天的上网界面是这个
It's text, you go find the text
是文字的你去找文字
But everything that can be done with words can be done with voice
但是凡是用文字的都可以用语音来达成
So we would expect that it should be possible to do these things with voice
所以我们会期待应该可以用语音来做这些事情
Of course, we also know that there are many interactions on the Internet today.
当然我们今天上网也了解有很多互动
which means we lost something
也就是说我们输了一些东西
net give me something
网路给我一些东西
have some interaction
有一些互动
This interaction is a dialogue of sound in terms of Silver
这个互动就银而言就是声音的对话
That can go a step further and be multimodal
那也可以再进一步可以是多模式的
Which means I might still be using touch
也就是说我可能同时还是用触控
There are also some keys
也有一些按键
then become a multimodal conversation
那么变成多模式的对话
That's what we're going to talk about today
那这也就是我们今天所要说的主题
That is, we can use voice commands
就是我们可以用语音的指令
through hand-held electronic devices
透过手持的一些电子设备
Then on the one hand, with the help of multimedia digital content
然后一方面借助多媒体数位内容
All with some voice narration to browse and search for information using the web
所有的一些語音旁白來瀏覽搜尋使用網絡的資訊
In a simple sentence
那用一句簡單的話來講
This means that what we are talking about is the voice version of Google-related technologies
這就是指我們要說的是語音版的Google相關的技術
That gets in simpler terms
那獲得用更簡單的話來說
It's voice unlimited Internet access
就是語音無限上網
that's what i'm going to talk about today
那就是我今天要說的主題
ok so how about the beginning
好 那麼一開始呢
Let's show you first
我們先給各位看一下
What does the sound signal look like
聲音訊號是長怎樣的
how we analyze it
我們如何分析它
Everyone knows that sound is sound waves in the air
各位了解聲音是空氣中的聲波
we can use a microphone
我們可以用一支麥克風
turn it into an electrical signal
把它轉成電的訊號
The signal of electricity is the cold and heat of a time
電的訊號說出來就是一個時間的寒暑
like this
像這樣
This time we go further
這個時候我們再進一步
Convert the electrical signal into a pile of hours and enter it into the computer
把電的訊號轉成一堆時數進入電腦
For example
舉例來講
This short signal is actually a point
這一小段的訊號其實就是一個點
one point
一個點
Then I will turn these points into hours
那我就把這些點變成一個個的時數
The computer can handle the time
時數電腦就可以處理了
This is what we call a voice signal
這就是我們說的語音訊號
what does it look like
它到底長怎樣呢
us
我們
Let's look at a few examples
我們看幾個例子
For example, this is an example of some vowels
譬如說這個是一些母音的例子
You can see, for example, this is E
各位可以看到譬如說這個是E
this is R etc.
這個是R等等
You immediately find that it has a common characteristic
你馬上發現它有個共同的特徵
That is, they are all cyclical
就是他們都是周期的
Then this cycle is the so-called pitch
那麼這個周期就是所謂的pitch
Jizhou
激州
Jizhou said it has a very clear physical meaning
激州說出來它有非常清楚的物理意義
is its inverse
就是它的倒數
It is what we call F0
就是我們講的F0
is the pitch that our ears hear
就是我們耳朵聽到的音高
So the immediate thing that comes to mind is
因此這個直接想到的事情就是
our four voices
我們的四聲
You guys know our fourth sound like R
各位知道我們的第四聲譬如說R
This pitch is slowly falling
這音高慢慢掉下來
As time goes on
隨著時間
The horizontal axis is time
這橫軸是時間
what does this mean
這什麼意思呢
I'm the one who posted the music R
就是我發R這個音樂
its cycle
它的周期
move forward
越往前走
It cycle becomes bigger and bigger
它周期越變越大越變越大
So the pitch gets lower and lower
於是音高越變越低越變越低
Then it becomes R
那就變成R了
if i pronounce
如果我發音的時候
This cycle is getting shorter and shorter
這個周期越變越短
getting shorter
越變越短
it climbs up
它就上上爬了
that's the second sound wait
那就是第二聲等等
We call this voice Joy in Voice
這樣聲音我們稱為Joy in Voice
There are many purple sounds that look like this
有很多的紫音是長得像這邊這樣
this is a purple sound
這是一個紫音
sandwiched between two periodic vowels
夾在兩個周期性的母音的中間
It has no cycles at all and is like a bunch of noise
它完全沒有周期是像一堆雜訊一樣的
We call it Qingyin unvoiced
我們稱為傾音unvoiced
Of course Ziyin is not exactly Qingyin
當然紫音不完全是傾音
There are also like this purple tone is v
也有像這個紫音是v
It is also sandwiched between two periodic vowels
它也夾在兩個周期性的母音的中間
But it's also clearly cyclical
不過它也明顯是有周期的
Like this Violet v it's still scorching
像這個紫音v它仍然是灼音
if you understand this
如果了解這個的話
Let's look at the signal length of a sentence
我們看一句話的訊號長怎樣呢
like this
就像這樣
this is a sentence
這是一句話
Our total length is 0.1 seconds
我們總共這個長度是0.1秒
Then there are a total of eight segments of 0.8 seconds
那麼這邊總共有八段0.8秒
This sentence is should we chase
這句話是should we chase
you will see the first
你會看到第一個
This is Qingyin
這是傾音
it's out of cycle
這是沒有周期的
this is un
這是un
It is clear that there is a cycle, etc.
很清楚的有周期的等等
This is a light tone, there is no period
這是輕音 是沒有週期的
This A is clearly periodic, etc.
這個A很清楚的是有週期的等等
That's our signal
那這樣就是我們一句話的訊號了
How do we analyze such a signal
這樣的訊號我們如何分析它
Of course, there are many ways to analyze
當然有很多種分析的方法
However, one of the most basic methods of analyzing signals
不過分析訊號最基本的一個方法
is to analyze its frequency
就是分析它的頻率
Then analyze the frequency
那麼分析頻率這件事情
then the simplest idea
那麼最簡單的想法
I think it can be explained like this
我覺得是可以這樣解釋
It seems that in the phasor of the three-dimensional space that we are very familiar with
就是好像我們很熟悉的三度空間的相量裡面
A phasor I can use three mutually perpendicular bases
一個相量我可以用三個互相垂直的基底
Ijk spread it out
Ijk把它展開
The three phasors
那這三個相量
Each of the three perpendicular bases has a component
這三個垂直的基底上各有一個分量
is the ADC
就是ADC
So I can write like this
因此我就可以寫成這樣
Of course, these three bases don't have to be like that.
那這三個基底當然不是一定要那樣
we can move it
我們可以隨便動它
like turn it around
譬如說把它轉一轉
if a turn
如果一轉
This Ijk is converted into iProng JProng KProng
這個Ijk就轉成iProng JProng KProng
when i turn like this
我這麼一轉的時候
My weight has also changed
我的這些個分量也都改變了
Although my phasor
雖然我的相量
is the same as A
是相同的A
Then such a conversion relationship
那这样的一个转换的关系
In fact, we analyze the frequency
其实我们分析频率的
this
这个
This Fuji conversion is exactly the same thing
这个富士转换也就是这么一回事
It's just a sign we're thinking now
只不过我们现在想的一个讯号
is very big
是非常大的
it spreads out across the timeline
它展开在整个时间轴上
Therefore
因此呢
it's on this T1T2T3
它在这个T1T2T3上面
have these values
有这些值
as if on these bases
就好像在这些个基底上
There are these components that are the same
有这些个分量是一样的
So why?
那么因此呢
When we do a Fuji conversion
当我们做一个富士转换
expand this signal to
把这个讯号展开到
When this frequency goes up
这个频率走上去的时候呢
I'm on every now
我现在每这个上
This converts every
这个转换每一个
every point becomes a frequency
每一点变成一个频率
In other words, a cos has different frequencies
或者说就是一个cos有不同的频率
Then there are these values
那上面一样有这些值
that means like
那意思就好比
I call it these
我把它这些
After turning these bases around
这些个基底转了一转之后
I regain the weight
我重新得到这些分量
So what this says above is
因此这上面所说的就是
in this signal
这个讯号里面的
components of each frequency
每一个频率的成分
how much each
各是多少
Then we call this frequency
那这个我们就称为频率
relatively
相对呢
this one just now
刚才这个呢
is the so-called real
就是所谓的实
With this understanding
有了這個了解之後
let's go back now
我們現在回來看
I want to analyze the sentence just now
我要分析剛才這句話
what to do
那怎麼辦
you can imagine my signal
你可以想像我的訊號
always changing
隨時在改變
For example, here is
譬如說這邊是
looks like this
是長得像這樣的
here is
這邊是
A looks like this
A長得像這樣的
how do i analyze it
我如何分析它呢
I have to analyze it piece by piece
我只好一小段一小段來分析
I can analyze this short paragraph
這小段我可以分析到
this frequency
這個頻率
frequency of A etc.
A的頻率等等
So what we can do
因此我們可以做的事情
just put this signal
就是把這個訊號
Take a small piece and a small piece to do it separately
一小段一小段分別拿來做
Fuji conversion
富士轉換
Each converted result
每一個轉換出來的結果
I draw it as a line
我把它畫成一條線
use its black and white or color
用它的黑白或者是顏色
to show its height
來呈現它的高低
as if it was like this one by one
就好像它是這樣的一個一個的
because every conversion
因為每一個轉換
Actually it's like this
其實是一個這樣子的
graph at this frequency
這個頻率上的圖
then i am actually
那我其實就是
A lot of these pictures are lined up here
一大堆這個圖排隊排在這
I just use the color for its height
我就把它的高低用顏色
or in black and white
或者黑白來呈現
become like this
就變成這樣
that kind of
那這樣的
Two-dimensional graph becomes a two-dimensional graph
二维的图 变成一个二维的图
This horizontal axis is the original time
这个横轴就是原来的时间
same time as this time
跟这个时间是一样的
and the vertical axis becomes frequency
而纵轴就变成频率
So it is a two-dimensional graph
于是就是二维的一个图
We call it spectrogram
我们称为spectrogram
maybe a food chart
或许可以叫做食品圖
we can give an example
我们可以举个例子
use just right
用刚才 对
There's one more thing
这还有一件事情就是
there's some really high places on this
这上面有一些特别高的地方
The components of these frequencies are particularly large
就这些频率的成分特别大
These are the times when we speak
这些就是我们在发声的时候
inside our mouth
在我们口腔里面
some frequencies of vocal resonance
发声共振的一些频率
after having this
有了这个之后
Let's look back at that sentence now
我们现在回头看一段才那句话
that sentence
那一句话
we just said
我们刚才说
This is the total sentence from the beginning to the end
这个从头到尾总共是这句话
Then each segment is 0.1 seconds
那么每一段是0.1秒
I'm redrawing it now
我现在重新画一次
put this horizontal axis
把这一段横轴
compress it into a paragraph
把它压缩变成一段
from here to here
就从这边到这边
That's what I just said
就是刚才的那句话
So this sentence is still should we chase
所以这句话仍然是should we chase
But I'll pull up the heavy shaft first
但是我先把重轴拉高
So the picture just now becomes here
因此刚才的图就变成在这里
So this is the signal on the timeline
所以这个就是在时间轴上的讯号
just an axis flag
刚才的一个轴旗
Between the two lines is an axis flag.
两条线中间就是一个轴旗了
It's packed into a pile.
里面挤成一堆了就是了
I draw the same timeline here
同样的这个时间轴我画在这里
The upper axis is my frequency
上面这个轴就是我的频率
The picture above is my time spectrum
上面这个图就是我的时频谱
we can see
我们就可以看到
For example, this is
譬如说这个是
Its time signal looks like this
它的时间上的讯号长这样
Its frequency is like this
它的频率上是长这样的
this is a thing
这个是物
things like this
物是这样的
it has axis flags
它有轴旗
Here things just become like this and so on
这边就物就变成这样等等
This is what we use time spectrum to analyze
这就是我们用时频谱来分析
What about another step?
那再一步呢
we just said
我们刚才说到
the top of these parts
这些个顶尖的这个部分
is the resonance frequency
是发生共振的频率
is that each point has a value
是每一点有一个值
then i can connect it
那我可以把它连起来
this is an area
这就是一个区域
If I draw this
我如果把这个画出来的话
just this example
就这个例子
you can see
各位可以看到
This is another word
这也是这是另外一句话了
but
但是呢
Below mine is the signal on its timeline
我的这个底下是它的时间轴上讯号
Above is its time spectrum
上面是它的时频谱
Then I can actually take these four resonant frequencies
那我其实可以把这四个发生共振的频率
Draw four curves
畫出來是四條曲線
Then we can see that at these frequencies
那麼我們可以看到在這些頻率
is the resonance frequency
是發生共振的頻率
And it with each tone of time
而它隨著時間每一個音
this sentence is this sentence
這句話是這句話
The resonant frequency of each sound is changing
每一個音它的共振頻率是在改變的
Okay, what I just told you is
好 剛才講的給各位看的是
voice on paper
紙上的聲音
Below we show you a real voice
底下我們給各位看一個真實的聲音
this is a sentence
這是一句話
we can first hear what it is
我們可以先聽一次它是什麼
This bus does not arrive at National Taiwan University
這班車到不到台灣大學
That's what's underneath
那底下這個就是
The bottom piece is what we just saw
底下這一塊就是我們剛才看到的
signal unfolded in time
在時間上展開來的訊號
That piece in the middle is what we just saw
那中間這一塊就是我們剛才看到的
food recipes
食品譜
we see every note of it
我們看到它每一個音
what it looks like in frequency
它的在頻率上的長相
What about the distribution of its different frequencies
那它的不同頻率的分佈的情形
Then these four four color curves
那麼這四條四個顏色曲線
is its four resonant frequencies
就是它的四個共振的頻率
that's up there
那上面就是
is the reciprocal of its period
是它的周期的倒數
that is pitch
也就是音高
You see that this bus can't arrive
你看到這是這班車到不到
You can see that this is less than
你可以看到這是這個到不到
This is the fourth sound
這個是第四聲到不到
The second one will arrive more smoothly and so on.
第二個到就會比較平緩等等
This is Taiwan, this is a university, etc.
這是台灣 這是大學等等
we can listen again
我們可以再聽一次
This bus does not arrive at National Taiwan University
這班車到不到台灣大學
We can also give an example
我們也可以舉個例子
For example, let's see, for example, what is the sound here?
譬如說我們看譬如說這個音到這裡是什麼呢
and
和
about sound
約的音
if here to here
如果這邊到這邊
The next thing is to learn
接起來的就是學
you know what it is from here to here
你知道這裡到這裡是什麼呢
Taiwan
台灣
OK
OK
What I want to show you is this Tao
我想要給各位看的是這個道
It doesn't look like this way
跟這個道長得很不像
Because of the call behind this
因為這個後面接的撥嘛
so it's already you heard it's going to dial
所以它已經你聽到它要接撥了
What about this way?
這個道呢
What if you look inside
那你如果看這裡面的話呢
kind of like
有一點像
Looking at its spectrum, it looks a bit like
看它的頻譜有一點像
You can see that the pitch is also much different
你看這個音高也差很多
What about this description?
這個說明呢
even in the same sentence
即使是同一句話裡面
The same person speaks two identical sounds
同一個人講兩個相同的音
is very different
是差很大的
we can pull it out a bit
我們可以把它拉開來一點看
for example
就是譬如說
this is less than
這是到不到
What if I pull it out to a certain extent?
我如果再拉開拉到一個程度之後呢
you can see its cycle
你可以看到它的周期
This cycle is very clear
這個周期是很清楚的
Then there is a lot of difference between the two before and after.
那麼前後兩個就差很多了
etc.
等等
good
好
The above passage is for you to understand
以上這段呢是讓各位了解一下
what sound do we see
我們所看到的聲音是怎樣的
good
好
What I want to tell you next is
底下呢要跟各位說的是
How do we let machines recognize human voices
我們怎麼樣讓機器來辨識人的聲音
then we immediately
那麼我們馬上
The voice recognition that comes to mind on the Internet seems to be like this
上想到的語音辨識好像是這樣一回事
this is a sound
這是一段聲音
today's weather is very good
今天的天氣非常好
For example, a short period of time is a lot of hours
譬如說這裡面一小段就是很多的時數
I got these answers by general calculus
我經過一般演算得到這些答案
But the basement is not so easy
不過天下室沒這麼容易
because you immediately understand
因為你馬上了解
Each of our sounds has many phonetic characters
我們的每一個音都有很多統音字
Just based on what sounds these are
光是根據這些是什麼聲音的話
You immediately think why this is not the gene of gold
你馬上想到這為什麼不是黃金的基因
Why isn't this the day of the meal?
這為什麼不是天飯的天呢
Of course because we all know when we hear
當然是因為我們人聽的時候都知道
why do people know
人為什麼都知道呢
because we know the context
因為我們有知道前後文
We also know these words in our heads
我們腦袋裡面也知道這些詞
So what a machine is going to do must also do these things
因此要機器做的必然也需要做這些事
That is, we need to put all kinds of language knowledge into the computer.
就是我們需要把各種的語言知識放進電腦裡面來
At least one of these is a dictionary
這裡面至少包括一個是詞典
one is grammar
一個是文法
The dictionary told me that it is connected with this sound
詞典告訴我說跟這個音連在一起
there is a word called today
有一個詞叫做今天
Grammar tells me that this word goes with this word
文法告訴我說這個詞跟這個詞連在一起
can become a phrase etc.
可以變成個片語等等
We humans actually know based on this
我們人其實聽也是根據這個才知道
this is not gold
這個不是黃金
this is not heaven
這個不是天飯
The same computer has something like this
同樣的電腦也有這樣的事
Therefore we need to take this knowledge
因此我們需要把這些知識
integrated with these signals
跟這些訊號整合在一起
that's what we're going to say
這就是我們底下要說的事
how to do this
怎麼做這件事呢
So let's start with the basics
那麼我們先講最基本的
sound signal
我們把聲音的訊號
Divided into different patterns to see
分成不同的pattern來看
For example
舉例來講
Let's say I want to recognize 10 sounds from 0 to 9
假設我要辨識0到9的10個聲音
position sound comes in
位置的聲音進來
My first step is to take its features
我第一步先取它的特徵
then the characteristic is
那麼特徵是指
bunch of numbers
一堆數字
wrap it up as a quantity
把它兜成一個項量
then follow the signal
然後隨著訊號向前走
I measure each item one by one
我就一個一個的項量
become a line of items
變成一排項量
sequence of items
我們稱為項量的序列
This sequence of items represents the sound
這個項量序列代表這個聲音
Then I went to compare with the model
然後我去跟模型比對
to make a decision
來做決定
what is the model
模型是什麼呢
Then if we recognize 10 sounds from 0 to 9
然後我們如果辨識0到9的10個聲音
I want 10 models
我要有10个模型
There is a model for each sound
每一个音有一个模型
They were also trained on known sounds, respectively.
他们分别也是用已知的声音去训练的
So the spirit model has to tell him these things
因此灵的模型要告诉他这些东西
These voices are spirit
这些声音都是灵
He uses their extracted feature sequence
他就用他们的抽出来的特征序列
To train the stored model
去训练存摊那个模型来
Then do this comparison
然后做这个比对
So here we have to explain
那么这里面我们要先解释一下
why feature
为什么要做特征
Once upon a time, my father, Sun Yuan, had a very good analogy
从前父亲孙院是有个非常好的比喻
He said I saw a man on the road
他说我在路上看到一个人
I want to judge whether he is a man or a woman
我要判断他是男的还是女的
I just look at his hair and his clothes
我只要看他的头发跟他的衣服
89 ignore 10
89不理10
Occasionally make a mistake
偶尔会错那个没办法
That hair and clothes are characteristic
那头发跟衣服就是特征
if i take a photo
我如果拍一张相片
Capture every bit of black and white
把每一点黑黑白白的颜色都拍出来
then count
然后去算
I can't tell if he's a man or a woman
可能还算不出来他是男的还是女的
But I knew it when I saw the clothes
可是我一看衣服就知道了
the same reason
同样的道理
We want the feature to be the same
我们希望的特征也是这样
You see how complicated it was just taught
各位看到刚刚训绍那么复杂
The same path looks completely different
同样的道就长得完全不一样
i can't rely on that
我不能靠那个
I want to grab features
我要抓特征
So what is this characteristic?
那麼這個特徵是怎樣的呢
Let's take another example
我們再舉個例子來看
We are actually like what we just said
我們其實就像剛才講的就是這樣
the signal is here
這訊號在這裡
Let me take this paragraph as an example, there are 512 points here
我拿這一段譬如說這邊有512個點
I do a calculation to get a series of numbers
我做個演算得到一系列的數字
Arrange it into an item called O1
把它排成一個項量叫做O1
I'll move this over later
待會我把這個移過來一點
Calculate these 512 points and get another item
算這512個點再得一個項量
get these numbers too
也是得這些數字
Get the second quantity called O2 O3 and so on
得到第二個項量叫做O2 O3等等
The signal then becomes a row of terms
於是這個訊號就變成一排項量
This is what we call the eigenvalue
這就是我們講的特徵項量
What's in it is not easy to explain here
這裡面是什麼不太容易在這裡解釋
but think of it this way
不過可以這樣想
first we know
第一個我們知道
scientists have long understood
科學家很早就了解
The human ear listens to the sound is to listen to the frequency
人耳朵聽聲音是在聽頻率
And listen to the frequency
而且是聽一段一段的頻率
Then we do the same here
那我們這裡同樣做這件事
That is to capture the signal in each frequency band
也就是把每一個頻段裡面的訊號抓出來
The second we also know
第二個我們也知道
The sound we make is R or U or G or T
我們發的聲音是R還是U是G還是T
because of our accent
是因為我們的口音
different shape
形不一樣
So the pure-tooth relationship is very important
因此純齒蛇的關係是非常重要的
In fact, we refer to these relations
我們事實上是把這些關係
only possible in these numbers
僅可能呈現在這些數字裡面
So how big is this phasor?
那這個相量有多大呢?
actually quite big
其實是相當大
Basically about 39 is about
基本上大約39為左右
is a very long, large phasor
是非常長的一個大的相量
Okay, with this understanding
好 有了這個了解之後呢
We probably know how these phasors come from
我們大概知道這些相量是這樣子來的
So the next question is what are these models like?
那下一個問題這些模型是怎樣的
then let's briefly explain
那我們簡單解釋一下
What is a model?
模型是什麼呢?
There are many models today
今天有很多種模型
But the most commonly used and generally successful
不過最普遍使用而普遍成功的
The so-called Hidden Markov Model
就是所謂的隱藏式馬可夫模型
Headed Mark Model
Headed Mark Model
Then let's explain this model in very simple language
那這個模型我們用非常簡單的語言來解釋它
It is a series of states of sound
它就是一系列的聲音的狀態
string it up
把它串起來
For example
舉例來講
If I want to recognize 10 sounds from 0 to 9
如果我要辨識0到9的10個聲音的話
Then 0 has a model of 0
那麼0有0的模型
1 in 1 model
1有1的模型
For example
舉例來講
Assuming this is a model of 6
假設這是6的模型
When I make the sound of 6
在我發6的聲音的時候
obviously
顯然是
The signal is preceded by a change of le
訊號在改變的前面是le
middle may be e
中間可能是e
may be followed by o
後面可能是o
We tried the signal keeps changing
我們試過訊號不斷改變
From 6 to 6 state
由有6變成6的狀態
to describe the different sounds
來描述不同的聲音
what are these
那這些是什麼呢
These are the feature quantities we just mentioned.
就是我們剛才那些特徵項量
You remember we have O1 O2 O3 here
你記得我們這邊有O1 O2 O3
are my feature quantities
都是我的特徵項量
then you can imagine
那你可以想像呢
maybe my front
也許我這個前面
What about the three O12 O3?
這個這三個O12 O3呢
is to describe the sound of this e
是描述這個e的聲音的情形
Then 4567 may be the case of 2
那4567可能是2的情形
8 could be 3 and so on
8可能是3等等
but you can understand right away
但是你馬上可以了解
It's okay when we send 6
我們發6的時候是可以
6 can also be 6
6也可以6
Can be long or short
可長可短
Each sound in the middle can be long or short
中間的每一個音都可長可短
So actually you can imagine
因此其實你可以想像
Every state here
這裡面每一個狀態
It can also be long or short
也一樣是可長可短的
So how to describe this phenomenon that can be long or short?
那如何描述這個可長可短的現象呢
Then we will use probability to illustrate it
那我們就用機率來說明它
So for example
因此舉例來講
we will have
我們這邊就會有
This means that if the previous O1 is in 1
這個就表示說我如果前面一個O1是在1裡面
The probability that the next O2 is still in 1
下一個O2還在1裡面的機率
And this is the O3 in front of me in 1
而這個就是我前面一個O3在1裡面
But the probability of the next O4 reaching 2, etc.
可是下面一個O4到了2裡面的機率等等
what is this for
那這是幹什麽呢
This is what we call the state transition probability
這是我們所謂的狀態轉移機率
In other words let's take for example
換句話說我們舉個例子
Suppose this is 0.1
假設這個是0.1
If this is 0.9
這個是0.9的話
I mean if I'm O3 it's 1
我意思是說我如果是O3是1
What about O4?
那麽O4呢
9 Chengdu is 2
9成都是2
That is to say, I am in 1
也就是說我在1裡面
1 to 1 becomes 2
1到1就會變成2
Because it pops up 90% of the time
因為它有9成都會跳出來
So 1 must be very short
所以1一定是很短的
Conversely
反過來呢
if this is 0.9
如果這是0.9
What if this is 0.1?
這是0.1的話呢
that means say
那就表示說
What if O1 is 1
如果O1是1的話呢
Then O28 is still 1
那O28成還是1
90% or 1
9成還是1
This is still 1
這個還是1
You can imagine that it takes about 9 times for 1 to become 2 and so on
你可以想像大概要9次1才会变成2等等
tell me these odds
这些几率就告诉我说
How can they be long or short
他们如何可长可短
But these are just chances
但是这些都只是几率
not necessarily
不是一定的
they are all random
他们都是随机的
can be changed
是可以变的
they don't have a certain value
他们没有一个一定的值
on the other hand
另一方面
Suppose I know that O1 is inside 1
假设我知道O1在1里面
Do I know what the phasor length of O1 is?
我是不是就知道O1的相量长怎样呢
i don't know
我其实不知道
Let's take the inside of O1 just now
我们就以刚才O1里面
For example, the X1 in O1
譬如说O1里面的这个X1
this is a value
这是一个值而言
what will happen to it
它会怎样
What about the X1?
那个X1呢
it can be like this
它可以是这样的
means that it can be this value
意思是说它可以是这个值
also this value
也是这个值
It will be all right
都可以
just the odds are different
只是几率不同而已
This is a probability distribution
这是一个几率的分布
In other words we completely
换句话说我们完全
Even if O1 is in 1
就算O1在1里面
I have absolutely no idea how much the X1 will be
我完全不知道X1会是多少
i just let it
我只是让它
It has different values
它在不同的值都有
Both may be high or low
都可能几率有高有低
It's more likely to see this here
在这里看这个几率比较大
This chance is relatively small
这个几率比较小
that is it
如此而已
what if it's in 2 or 3
如果它是在2或者3里面会怎样呢
also the same
也是一样
but each value can
但每个值都可以
The distribution of the probability of its value is just different
值它的几率的分布不一样而已
This shows how diverse our signals are
这个说明我们的讯号是如此的多元
very varied
变化非常的丰富
like you just saw
就像你刚才看到
same two to less than two to
同样两个到不到两个到
it's just different
它就是不一样
then in this case
那么在这个情形之下
in each state
那每一个状态里面
Each value can have this many probability distributions
每一个值都可以有这么多几率分布
what to do
怎么办
What we usually do is
我们通常的做法就是
Approach it with a high wire probability
用一把高丝几率来趋近它
you may understand
那各位可能了解
Kose is a most standard probability model
高丝是一个最标准的几率模型
We just give it an average
我们只要给它一个平均值
with its fatness
跟它的肥瘦度
it has to be like that
它就一定是那个样子
So no matter how long this
因此不管这个长怎样
I can even get close to it with a Kose
我都可以用一把高丝几来趋近它
What about this way?
那用这个方式呢
I get a say 6
我就得到一个譬如说6
6 models
6的模型
There are a lot of parameters in this model
這個模型裡面有一大堆參數
For example, these probabilities
譬如說這些機率
Gauss's and so on
這裡面的高斯的這些等等
These parameters are all trainable
這些參數都是可以訓練的
I just need to give the machine enough 666666
我只要給機器夠多的666666
tell it it's 6 words
告訴它這是6的話
I can get all these papers of these 6 models
我就可以把這些6的模型的這些紙都求出來
when i have another voice called 6
當我有另外一個聲音叫做6的話
I throw its phasor in
我把它的相量丟進去
can count its chances
可以算它的機率
The probability of 6 should be high and so on
6的機率應該是很高的等等
This is the model we are talking about
這就是我們講的這個模型
Well, what I just said is limited to
好不過剛才講的僅限於
Suppose I recognize only 10 tones from 0 to 9
假設我辨識0到9的10個音而已
that is easier
那是比較容易的
What we really want to recognize is the continuous speech of great wisdom
我們真正要辨識的是大智慧的連續語音
What is the so-called great wisdom?
那所謂大智慧是什麼
Do you know the commonly used words in Chinese?
各位知道譬如說中文的常用詞
We can probably assume 60,000
我們也許可以假設是6萬吧
Then there are about 60,000 common words in English.
那英文的常用字大概也是6萬吧
So, in any of my random sounds
所以呢我隨便的一個音裡面
does it belong to a certain word
它屬於某一個字呢
It has 60,000
它有6萬個嘛
Then they talked consecutively
然後呢他們是連著講的
In a word, you don't know it is
一句话讲起来你不曉得它是
How many words are there in the middle?
中间有几个字几个词
I don't know where it's disconnected in the middle
中间哪里断开我都不知道的
how do i deal with this problem
这个问题我怎么处理
you can imagine
你可以想象
suppose my voice comes in
假设我的声音进来
Like I just did it's feature
我一样就刚才做了它的特征
Phasor After getting a series of phasors
相量得到一系列的相量之后
Suppose the voice is the sentence
假设这个声音是这句话
This is a speech
This is a speech
how can i tell it apart
我怎么分辨它呢
The first point is that I try to find a way
第一点就是我想办法
since this is english
既然这是英文
I took all the possible basic sounds of English
我就把英文的所有可能的基本音
find out
找出来
There may be around 40 basic sounds in English
英文的基本音可能在40个左右
So I took these basic notes
于是我就把这些基本音
Create one for each basic tone
每一个基本音都建一个
The model just mentioned
刚才讲的模型
The model formed by these basic sounds
这些基本音所构成的模型
is what we call an acoustic model
就是我们所谓的声学模型
For example, in this sentence
譬如说这句话里边
These are the basic sounds spelled out
就是这些个基本音拼出来的
So therefore we want my acoustic model
那么因此我们希望我的声学模型
can tell me
可以告诉我说
In this sound are these basic tones
这个声音里面就是这些个基本音
In fact, what we do is far more complicated than this
其实我们做的是远比这个复杂
Because we found that the basic tone
因为我们发现这个基本音
not just one model
并不是只有一个模型
as long as the front is different
只要前面不一样
The back is different
后面不一样
it's just different
它就是不一样的
Did we just see that
我们刚才看到那个道不道
The way ahead is different from the way behind
前面的道跟后面的道就是不一样
because of that way
因为那个道
It will be different if there is one behind the front road.
前面的道后面接了一个不就不一样了
So we actually want to see the difference between the front and the back
因此我们其实是要看前面后面不一样
are different
都算不一样
So we're using what's called a triple-sonic
所以我们用的是所谓的三连音速
Tri-Fone
Tri-Fone
Suppose there are 40 basic sounds in English
假设英文的基本音是40个的话
how many models do i need
我需要多少个模型呢
40 to the third power so many kinds
40的三次方那么多种
assuming i know the sounds
假设我知道这些音的话
This time I can use a dictionary
这回我可以用一个词典
The dictionary told me that the spelling of these sounds is this word
词典告诉我说这几个音拼起来是这个字
The spelling of these sounds is this word
这几个音拼起来是这个字
etc.
等等
so i can get the answer
于是我就可以得到答案了吗
the answer is not
答案不是
We know that this world is inferior to consciousness ten to eighty-nine
我们知道这个天下不如意识十至八九
why
为什么呢
because you can immediately imagine
因为你马上可以想象
How similar is this sound to this sound
这个音跟这个音多么像
If we let our ears distinguish
如果让我们人耳朵去分别
It's not easy to tell, right?
還不容易分辨對呢
It is more difficult for machines to distinguish between
機器更不容易分辨對
So the machine can only tell me
因此機器只能告訴我說
The sound is probably this
這個音很可能是這個
probably this
很可能是這個
each with a score
各有一個分數
Then the highest score
那麼到底分數最高
that's right
那個就對嗎
not necessarily
也不見得
So after getting a bunch of tones
因此得到一大堆音之後
Can spell out many miraculous words
可以拼出很多奇蹟怪怪的字出來
then what should we do
那怎麼辦呢
Then we need to have a
那我們需要有一個
so-called language model
所謂的語言模型
he told me
他告訴我說
In fact, only these three words together
其實只有這三個字連起來
is the most smooth sentence
才是最順的一句話
why
為什麼呢
he can count
他可以算
The word appears in
這個字出現在
Chances of giant hands
巨手的機率
then after the word
然後這個字後面
The probability of receiving this word
接這個字的機率
then these two words
然後這兩個字
The probability of following this word, etc.
後面接這個字的機率等等
multiply them all
把他們全部乘起來
is the probability of this sentence
就是這句話的機率
If the probability of the sentence is high
如果這句話的機率高的話
I feel like saying
我就覺得說
This is relatively smooth
這個是比較順的
So these are what we call language models
那這些就是我們所謂的語言模型
For example
譬如說呢
This is the probability that two words are connected
這是兩個字相連的機率
double grammar
我們稱為雙連文法
This is the probability of connecting three words
這是三個字相連機率
the first two
前面兩個
I will take this chance later
後面會接這個機率
what we call triplicate grammars etc.
我們稱為三連文法等等
What about these language models?
那這些個語言模型呢
Of course how did it come about?
那當然怎麼來的呢
I can use a text database
我是可以用一個文字資料庫
For example, if you go online, you can capture a database of 10 million words.
那譬如說上網可以抓一千萬字的資料庫
to count the odds
去數這些機率
I can work out the odds
我可以算出這些機率出來
These probabilities are called language models
這些機率就是所謂的語言模型
what about after this
那有了這個之後呢
This time I have a better way to string the sounds together
這回我比較有辦法可以把這些音通通串起來
I have a better way of knowing what it is
我比較有辦法知道它是什麼
what's the matter
什麼話了
So what about the language model just now?
那麼剛才講這個語言模型的這件事呢
I use the example below
我用底下這個例子
Maybe it's easier for Chinese people to imagine
也許是中文的各位可能更容易想像
here is a sentence
這裡有一句話
This sentence is called
這句話叫做
Two people in Taitung are missing
豪語不斷台東兩人失蹤
This is a sentence from the TV news
這個是電視新聞裡面一句話
but what?
那但是呢
Because many sounds are similar
因為很多音都很像
I can spell a lot of weird words in no time
我馬上可以拼成很多奇怪的字來
strange word come
奇怪的詞來
For example, say Haoyu
譬如說豪語呢
It seems to be temple language
好像是廟語
Also like pottery
也好像是陶藝
so constantly
那麼不斷呢
also looks like gratuitous
也很像是無端
What about Taitung?
台東呢
much like too much wait
很像是太多等等
So many possible words can be spelled out
因此可以拼出很多的可能詞出來
We draw it into a graph called a word graph
我們把它畫成個圖叫做詞圖
The horizontal axis in this graph is time.
這個圖裡面橫軸就是時間
any line is some possible word
任何一條線都是某一個可能詞
between two points
在某兩點之間
Our vertical axis has no special meaning
我們縱軸沒有特別的意義
just connect all the words in there
只是把所有可語連在那裡連起來
Each path here is a possible answer
這裡每一條路徑都是一個可能的答案
We need to know that there is only this
我們要知道其實只有這條
is the correct answer
才是正確答案
nothing else is right
別的都不對
That's the role of the language model
那就是語言模型的角色
We want him to figure it out and tell me
我們希望他算出來告訴我說
The two missing in Taitung
這個毫與不斷台東兩人失蹤
The odds are much higher than this
這個機率是遠高於這個
What escape is too heavy for no reason, etc.
什麼逃逸無端太重什麼的等等
Then this is the function we just talked about
那這就是我們剛才講的這個功能
Then this needs to be trained with a text database.
那這個要用文字資料庫來訓練
Then this needs to use the sound database for training, etc.
那這個要用聲音資料庫來訓練等等
Well, after understanding this
好 了解了這個之後
then we need to know the next thing
那麼我們要了解下一件事情
then you can notice all my arrows now
那你可以注意到我現在所有的箭頭
We all know this is coming
都知道這塊來了
what is this doing
這塊在幹嘛
He has a lot to do
他這一個人要做很多事
He took all the items in
他把所有的項量收進來
He also put this acoustic model
他也把這個聲學模型
take the words in
把詞點收進來
All languages ​​are included
語言文都收進來
Other profitable export complaints
他得輸出文句
This man is very powerful
這個人是很厲害的
This person is called a language model
這個人叫做語言模型
language decoding
叫做語言解碼
what is he doing
他在做什麼事呢
We use the following figure to explain
我們用底下一張圖來解釋
first thing is
第一件事情是
We're going to point the word now
我們現在要把詞點
build a number
建成一個數
word points
叫做詞點數
What's the meaning
什麼意思
for example
譬如說
s followed by a is called s
s 後面接a 叫做s
it's a word
這是一個詞
s followed by e
s 後面接e
This is speak
這個是speak
it's a word
這是一個詞
Here connect ch to speak
這邊接ch 變成speak
it's a word blah blah
這是一個詞等等等等
I assume that there are 60,000 common English words
我假設英文常用字是6萬個
My side is 60,000 words connected here
我這邊就是6萬個字通連在這裡
become a tree
變成一棵樹
any line on a tree
在樹上任何一條線
or a jug
或者說一條壺
is a Hidden Markov Model
就是一個隱藏式馬可夫模型
Because it's all a model
因為這都是一個模型
When you go to the end of every road is a word
當你每一條路走到底就是一個字
or a word
或者一個詞
what we call a leaf
我們所謂的一片葉子
a leaf on a tree
樹上一片葉子
So what?
那麼於是呢
I give us any voice
我給我們任何一段聲音
I'll start here
我就從這裡開始走起
Go all the way down to calculate the score for each path
一路向下走去計算每一條路徑的分數
So where does this score go
於是這個分數走到哪裡
I knew the signal here
我就知道到這個訊號這裡
is say what is the score
是say的分數是多少
What is the score of the speech when you come here, etc.
走到這邊是speech的分數是多少等等
Then why should I be a tree?
那我為什麼要做成一棵樹呢
That's because only in this way
那是因為唯有這樣
I can use the same unit without double counting
我才可以相同的單位應不用重複計算
For example, this speak and speech
譬如說這個speak跟speech
The road ahead is a good score
前面這條路都算好的分數
only the end here is different
只有最後這裡不一樣
get two points etc.
就得到兩個分數等等
After this we have to understand
這樣之後我們要瞭解
I don't know the score of a word until I finish walking
走完之後我才知道一個字的分數而已
That's because I'm a continuous voice
那因為我是連續語音
So a word is followed by all possible words
所以一個字後面要所有可能的字
so what will it be
因此會是怎樣呢
will be like this
會是這樣
The end of each word is connected to the next tree
每一個詞的尾端接下一棵樹
So let's say this has 60,000 common words
所以假設這個有六萬個常用字
Go to the end after every word
每一個字後面走到底
Just start picking the next tree
就開始接下面一棵樹
The tree has 60,000 leaves
這個樹有六萬個葉子
Go to the bottom and pick up the next tree, etc.
走到底又接下面一棵樹等等
So this is a primeval forest expanded by word point trees
所以這是一個由詞點樹展開的原始森林
There are thousands of numbers in it
裡面有千千萬萬個數
Then I'm going to find the answer in it
那我要在裡面找尋答案
Then this is what we have to do in the language code block just now.
那這就是我們剛才那一塊語言結碼要做的事
Okay, this probably explains how we recognize human voices.
好 這個大概解釋了我們如何辨識人的聲音
Next, I will talk about Chinese speech technology
底下要說一下的 中文的語音技術
Why is it the same as Western languages?
為什麼跟西方語言一樣呢
That's because our Chinese language structure is very special
那是因為我們中文的語言結構是很特別的
What about the first one?
第一個呢 方塊字
every word has its meaning
每一個字都有它的意思
And what we really mean by a sentence are words, not characters.
而我們真正講一句話的意思是詞 不是字
What does the word mean, and what does the word mean?
那詞的意思呢 又跟字的意思呢
sometimes relevant and sometimes irrelevant
是有的時候相關 有的時候無關
For example, our small bookstore is a store that sells books.
舉例來講呢 我們小的書店就是賣書的店
This means directly related
這個意思是直接相關的
University is not a big study
大學呢 並不是很大的學
But he has something to do with university and school.
但是呢 他跟大跟學都有關係
What about the bachelor? It's not a glowing stick.
那光棍呢 不是一個發光的棍子
But he probably has something to do with light and stick
不過呢 他大概跟光跟棍的關係
a little bit less
有一點很少了
Does the wind follow the flow?
是不是风跟流呢
it's harder to say
这就更难讲一点
so different words
所以不同的词
It has a complex relationship with the meaning of the word
它的跟字的含义是有复杂的关系的
so i see a word
所以我看到一个字
or hear a word
或者听到一个字
What exactly does that mean
到底是什么意思
This is quite complicated
这个是蛮复杂的
Furthermore, our Chinese words have no boundaries
再来我们中文的词是没有边界的
in the sentence
在句子里面
And even the definition of the word is not clear
而甚至于词的定义也不明确
For example, in this sentence
举例来说这句话里面
everyone see
各位看到
computer is a word
电脑是一个词
technology is a word
科技是一个词
is a word
是一个词
tech is a word
科技的是一个词
computer technology is a word
电脑科技是一个词
computer technology is also a word
电脑科技的也是一个词
which word is a word
到底哪一个词是一个词
actually
其实
definition is ambiguous
定义是不明确的
The words in everyone's mind are different
每一个人心里想的词是不一样的
Furthermore, many of our small words can be connected in series at will
再来我们的很多小词可以随意串联
become a big word
变成大词
For example, the terrorist attack in New York
譬如说纽约恐怖攻击事件
Our long words can be arbitrarily shortened into short words
我们的长词可以任意缩短变成短词
For example, Taiwan University has become too big
譬如说台湾大学变成太大
Then what
然后呢
some words can be split
一有的词是可以切开的
For example, Lee Teng-hui becomes former President Lee Teng-hui
譬如说李登辉变成李前总统登辉
Then what
然后呢
You can take a bath and take a comfortable big bath
洗澡可以洗了一个舒舒服服的大澡
Everyone should understand that a bath is not a thing
各位要了解澡不是一个东西
So instead of washing an apple
所以不是洗一个苹果
this is a bath
这是洗了一个澡
But this bath can be taken apart
但是这个澡是可以拆开来的
etc.
等等
Therefore, each of our words is independent and interesting like this
因此我们每个字都是这样子独立的有意思的
So new words are generated automatically every day
所以新词每天自动产生
For example, gasoline and electric palms
譬如说油电双掌
this is the new word
这就是新词
We don't need to define what it is
我们不需要定义它是什么
Everyone knows
每个人都知道
etc.
等等
Top too wind
顶太风
word everyone knows this time
这次每人都知道的词
But will they be in the dictionary
但他们会不会在词典里面
80% of them are not in the dictionary
词典里面八成是没有的
Therefore our words are infinite
因此我们的词是无限大的
We are unlikely to be inside a dictionary
我们不太可能在一个词典里面
contains all the words
包含所有的词
Did you notice when I just said
你注意到我刚才讲的时候
There must be a dictionary in this method
这方法里面都是要有词典的
But Chinese dictionaries are difficult to make
但是中文的词典是很难做的
the second
第二个
We also have a very special structure
我们还有一个很特别的结构
That is, we are word for word
就是我们是一字一音的
every word has a sound
每一个字有一个音
But the number of sounds is very small
但是音的种数是很少的
Everyone knows our Chinese
各位知道我们的华语
The total number of sounds is about 1300
音的總數大概是1300多個
We have at least 80,000 commonly used characters
我們有常用字至少是8萬個以上
More than 8000
8000個以上
Therefore, each sound can have many phonetic characters
因此每一個音可以有許多的統音字
have different meanings
各有不同的意義
so you hear a voice
所以你聽到一個聲音
don't know what word it is
並不知道它是什麼字的
then another point
那麼另外一點
we are tonal language
我們是有聲調的語言
I just said it
剛才已經說過了
so different tones give me different words
因此不同的聲調給我不同的字
different meaning
不同的意思
Let's take an example
我們舉個例子
you will understand immediately
你馬上瞭解
For example, the two sounds of one and ten
譬如說一跟十這兩個音
They all have four tones and many homophonic characters.
都是有四聲都有很多統音字的
We can make up a lot of words with unison
我們隨便拼湊就有很多統音的詞出來
For example
舉例來講
Here is a time, a time, a time, a time, a time
這邊的是一時一世一世一時一世一時
In fact, there are many, many
其實還有很多很多
I just give these few examples
我只是舉這幾個例子而已
you will understand
你就瞭解
if i don't know its tone
我如果不知道它的聲調的話
It's really hard for me to know what it's talking about
我真的不容易知道它在說什麼
Furthermore
再者
we have different voices
我們因為是不同的音
can form a myriad of words
可以組成千變萬化的詞
so our voice
因此我們的聲音
Grasp the sound inside from the sound
要從聲音來抓裡面的音
his difficulty is
他的難度是
quite high
相當高的
We actually have many words with the same pronunciation
我們其實還有很多完全同音的詞
You may never have felt
各位可能從來沒有感覺過
Because we don't have to worry about it when we talk
因為我們說話的時候是不用擔心這件事的
For example
舉例來講
The intersection of Research Institute Road and Zhongxiao East Road
研究院路跟中校東路相交的地方
Then of course what I'm talking about is this intersecting
那我講的當然是這個相交
You don't have to expect that intersection
你不必想到還會那個相交
etc.
等等
This is what we humans can do
這是我們人是可以這樣
machine you have to let the machine know
機器你得要讓機器知道
That is to say, our few limited tones
也就是說我們少數有限的音
Carries extremely rich linguistic messages
攜帶極為豐富的語言訊息
Then the hierarchical language unit of sound is Western language
那麼音的層次語言單位是西方語言
pinyin but not in the language
的拼音但語言所沒有的
Again, the order of our words in the play
再來我們的詞在劇裡面順序
is quite free
是相當自由的
give an example
舉一個例子來講
these few words
這幾個詞
I'm leaving at 6:30 tomorrow morning
明天早上6點半我要出發
These words form a sentence
這幾個詞構成一個句子
I mean everyone will understand right away
意思大家馬上都瞭解
but you know
但是各位可知道
How many ways are there?
有多少種說法嗎
at least these
至少有這些
I can be 6:30 tomorrow morning
我可以是明天早上6點半
i want to go
我要出發
Or I will leave at 6:30 tomorrow morning
也可以明天我早上要6點半出發
or wait and wait
或者等等等等都可以
So why?
那麼因此呢
Use Mandarin voice to search Chinese information
用國語的語音去搜尋中文資訊
what kind of problems
有些什麼樣的難題
then you can immediately think of
那麼你馬上可以想到的
The first is because the information network is alive
第一個就是因為資訊網路是活的
Chinese thoughts keep appearing every day
中文的心思每天不斷出現
And the mind is not in the dictionary
而心思不在詞典裡面
is difficult
便是困難
But what we are looking for is often heart words
可是我們要搜尋的常常是心詞
those are our keywords
那些就是我們的關鍵詞
For example
舉例來講
I want to order the top Taifeng Xiehuang Xiaolongbao
我要訂頂太封的謝皇小籠包
It is quite possible that the Internet is going to say that
這是很可能上網要說的是
But this thing is not in the dictionary
不過這個東西不在詞典裡面
This thing is not in the dictionary
這個東西也不在詞典裡面
Can you catch it just based on these sounds?
光是根據這些音你抓得到嗎
Wait these are examples of this
等等這些都是這個例子
Typhoon Nali
譬如說納利颱風
Definitely not in the dictionary
詞典裡面的鐵定是沒有的
But the keyword you want is this
但是你要的關鍵詞就是這個
these are keywords
這些都是關鍵詞
Words in user commands and target information
在者使用者指令跟目標資訊中的詞
often inconsistent
常常是不一致的
for example
舉例說
So say I'm looking for
因此說我要找
North Second High Road Conditions
北二高的路況
It is said on the Internet that there are too many vehicles on the Second Northern Expressway
網路上說北部第二高速公路目前車多
The machine needs to know this is this
機器要知道這個就是這個
otherwise you won't find
否則你就找不到
Different meanings
在者錯誤的斷詞常常造成不同的意義
For example, someone wants to go online to find a brain doctor.
舉例來講有人想上網去找腦科
He found a lot of brain
他找到一大堆腦科
But it doesn't look like a brain
可是一看去都不是腦科
why
為什麼呢
Because there is a word break boundary in the middle
因為這中間有一個斷詞的邊界
it is computer science
它是電腦科學
Some people want to go online to find folk land
有人想上網去找民間的土地
The folk belief is called the God of the Land
民間信仰叫做土地公
Then he went to find a lot of land owners
那麼他去找到一大堆都有土地公
But it's strange why the Landlord has a policy
但是很奇怪土地公為什麼有政策呢
you find out it wasn't
你就發現原來不是的
Because he's talking about public ownership of land and so on.
因為他講的是土地的公有政策等等
Of course, there are errors in speech recognition and so on.
那當然語音辨識還有錯誤等等
These are all the problems you can imagine
這些都是你可以想像到的難題
Well, the above paragraph explains about this sound recognition
好以上這段解釋關於這個聲音辨識
how to do it
怎麼做的
So we're going to go into this sound search
這樣我們要來進入這個聲音的搜尋
Explain what we mean by sound search
解釋一下我們講的聲音的搜尋
What is Voice Information Search
語音資訊搜尋是什麼
What is its relationship to text information search
它跟文字資訊搜尋的關係是什麼
This is the Google we know today
這個是我們今天所熟悉的Google
I enter a text command
我輸入一個文字指令
So what?
那於是呢
The machine gave me a lot of files
機器給我一大堆文件
The text file contains all the things I want
文字的文件裡面都有我要的東西
but we know
但是我們知道
All the instructions and documents
這個所有的指令也好文件也好
can it be voice
可以是語音嘛
so i can
所以呢我可以
Use text commands to find audio files
用文字的指令去找語音的文件
The so-called audio file is a piece of audio
所謂語音文件就是一段語音
or a multimedia file
或者說一段多媒體的文件
a piece of multimedia
一段多媒體
it contains speech but no text
它含語音但是不含文字
I have to rely on the voice signal inside
我必須要靠裡面的語音訊號
to judge the rocky beach
去判斷這個石灘
Then of course I can use voice commands to find text files
那當然我可以用語音指令去找文字文件
I can also use voice commands to find audio files
我也可以用語音指令去找語音文件
These three are different things
這三件是不同的事
three different questions
三個不同的問題
Technically there are different proper nouns to describe it
在技術上有不同的專有名詞來描述它
But we call it what we call audio search
不過我們都稱它為我們講的語音資訊搜尋
Among these three things, today is the easiest and most mature
這三件事裡面今天最容易最成熟的
It is the so-called voice search in the middle
就是中間這一件所謂的voice search
In other words, use voice commands to find text files
也就是說用語音指令來找文字文件
Why does it actually just take the original text instruction
為什麼它其實只是把原來的文字指令
Find a text file and add one in front of it
找文字文件這件事前面加一個
When the voice command comes in, I will convert it into text first
語音指令進來我先把它變成文字
Just do the same later
後面就一樣照做就好了
So like Google has its voice search
所以像Google就有它的voice search
that's what it is
那其實就是這樣
Add a voice interface in front of Google's existing entire Google, etc.
以Google現有的整個的Google前面加個語音的界面等等
But in fact you can learn about us today
但是事實上你可以了解我們今天
The main part of my talk today is the other two
我今天講的主要部分是另外這兩個
That is, if what I'm looking for is an audio file,
也就是如果我要找的是語音文件的話
Whether it's through voice commands
不管是用語音指令來找
or text commands
還是文字指令來找
No matter which one of them is basically
那不管這裡面的哪一種基本上
you imagine me to do things
你想像我要做事情
turn voice into text
先把聲音變成文字
Then I do a text search
之後我就做文字的搜尋
to find
去找
if you said it before
如果之前講的話
it seems easy
這好像不難
The biggest problem is
最大難題就是
identification must be wrong
辨識必然有錯誤
Our Speech Recognition Technology Today
我們今天的語音辨識技術
still have a ton of errors
仍然有一大堆錯誤
why wrong
為什麼錯誤
just now you can probably imagine
剛才你可能可以想像
We say that light cannot pour
我們講光是倒不到
The two are different
兩個倒就是不一樣的
so you need to know
所以你要知道
which signal is which word
哪個訊號是哪個詞
It's not easy
其實是不容易的
first thought was
第一個想到是
I can use word graph to reduce
我可以用詞圖減少
The impact of misidentification
辨識錯誤的影響
as if we just saw
就好像我們剛才看到
in one sentence
一句話裡面
I don't want to just recognize it as a sentence
我不要只把它辨識成為一句話
Because there may be a lot of typos in it.
因為這樣可能裡面錯很多字
But I can put all possible
但是我可以把所有可能的
List all the words and turn them into a picture
詞通通列出來變成一張圖
In this case
這樣的話
all my words i can take into account
我所有的詞我都可以考慮到
So the correct word is taken into account the chance
因此正確詞被考慮到機會
greatly increased
就大為增加
But
可是
This also adds a lot of wrong words
這個也同時增加大量的錯誤的詞
So I'm likely finding a bunch of wrong things
所以我很可能找到一堆錯誤的東西
while the correct word may still not be in it
而正確詞可能仍然不在裡面
especially the words outside the dot
尤其是詞點外的詞
it won't recognize it at all
它根本不會辨識出來
Of course I need a lot of calculations
當然我需要計算量什麼都很大
etc.
等等
There are many other ways
也存在很多別的方法
But I won't talk about this today
不過這個今天就不說了
let's talk about another thing
我們講另外一件事
What should I do if many words are not in the word points?
就是很多詞不在詞點裡面怎麼辦
In fact, this is easier to deal with
其實這個是比較容易處理的
Our usual approach today is to use so-called word units
我們今天通常辦法就是用所謂的詞詞單位
is a unit smaller than words
就是比詞還要小的單位
You immediately think that every language has its basic sounds
你馬上想到就是每一個語言都它基本音
Treat the basic sound as a unit
把那個基本音當成單位來做
also can
也就可以
For example
舉例來講
suppose it's a word
假設這是一個詞
W
W
It is made up of these four small basic sounds
它是這四個小的基本音所湊出來的
lexical units
它們都是所謂的詞詞單位
But since it's not in the dot
但是因為它不在詞點裡面
So it will not appear in the word map
所以它不會出現在詞圖裡面
This is a line of words in the word map
這個是詞圖裡面的一條一條的詞
they just don't have the word
它們就是沒有這個詞
Then these other ABCDs are also other word units
那其他這些ABCD也都是其他的詞詞單位
no
就沒有
But if you look closely, you'll see
但是你如果仔細看一看就會發現
I want this word is obviously hidden in this sub-word
是我要了這個詞明明隱藏在這個次詞裡面
So I just do the comparison at the subword level
所以我只要在次詞層次來做比對
it can be compared
它可以比對出來的
It doesn't matter if you don't recognize it
即使沒有辨識出來是沒有關係的
So when I'm looking for Obama
所以我要找歐巴馬的時候
Obama is in
歐巴馬在裡面
Although Obama is not in my dictionary
雖然我詞典裡面沒有歐巴馬
it doesn't matter
是沒有關係的
etc.
等等
the subunit
這個次詞單位
In fact different languages
其實不同的語言
The most suitable units are not the same
最適合的單位是不一樣的
There are also people who directly use data to push him to do data driven
也有人直接用數據去推他做data driven
That is to say, let the data tell me
也就是說讓data告訴我
Which is the best unit etc.
最好的單位是哪一種等等
good
好
Let's talk about
底下我們來說
Some recent examples of using voice for information search
這個用語音做資訊搜尋的近期的一些
Compare some examples of relevant research
比較相關的研究的一些例子
Most of this is what we did at National Taiwan University
這裡面多半是我們在台大所做的
So some simple examples
那麼一些簡單的例子
Let everyone know
讓各位了解一下
Then the biggest problem we mentioned just now is that the identification will be wrong.
那我們剛才講最大的問題就是辨識會錯誤
Then we can imagine
那麼我們可以想像成
This audio information search that most people want
這個多數人想的語音資訊搜尋
this is the picture
就是這張圖
There's a whole bunch of audio digital content over here.
這邊是一大堆的語音數位內容
Do sound recognition first
先做聲音的辨識
Turn every sentence into a word graph
把每一句話變成一個詞圖
When the user enters a command
當使用者輸入一個指令的時候
For example, he wants to find Obama
譬如說他要找歐巴馬
So we searched for the introduction
於是我們搜尋引進
Just find it in these largest word graphs
就在這些最大的一詞圖裡面去找
where is obama
哪裡有歐巴馬
This idea is basically reasonable
這個構想基本上是很合理的
just saying he has the biggest problem
只是說他有個最大的問題
Because he combines identification with search
因為他把辨識跟搜尋
into two units
變成兩個單元
Train them individually and connect them together
各自訓練好再把它串接起來
so misidentification leads to wrong search results
因此辨識錯誤就導致錯誤的搜尋結果
how good your search is
你的搜尋辦法再好
may not be able to recover from misidentification
未必能夠挽救辨識的錯誤
So what we think about is
因此我們想的事情是
How to break the frame of these two units connected in series
如何打破這兩個單元串接的框架
These two connect him forever
這兩個串接他永遠
Can't fix this error
無法解決這個錯誤的問題
So after we break it down
所以我們把它打破之後
rethink a thing
重新看成一件事
Integrative thinking to reduce the impact of misidentification
整合性的思考來減少辨識錯誤的影響
Let's give a few examples of this
我們舉幾個例子來說這件事
The first example is the so-called virtual correct feedback
第一個例子是所謂的虛擬正確回饋
The idea is that if you're looking for Obama
這個想法是說如果要找的是歐巴馬
Suppose you already know that there is really Obama in a certain sentence
假設你已經知道某一句裡面真的有歐巴馬的話
Then other possible sentences that are similar to him can get extra points
那麼其他可能的句子凡是跟他像的就可以加分
the idea is simple
這想法很簡單
The problem is how do I know which sentence is correct?
問題是沒有一句我怎麼知道哪一句是正確的呢
I have no idea
我不知道
This way I'm assuming I'm doing the first search first
這個辦法就是我假設我先做第一次搜尋
get a bunch of results
得到一堆結果
I become a search result
我成為出搜結果
Assuming the ex-en name inside is correct
假設裡面的前恩名是正確的
so what will it be
因此會是怎樣呢
like this
就像這樣
this is my command
這是我的指令
like Obama
譬如說歐巴馬
My machine got a bunch of results the first time I searched
我機器第一次搜尋就得到一堆結果
is the search result
就是出搜結果
The machine at least judges that they all look like Obama
機器至少判斷他們裡面好像都有歐巴馬的樣子
I don't show this result to the user
這個結果我不給使用者看
Because there are many mistakes in it
因為其裡面錯很多
I'll take the ex-en name in this first
我就先拿這個裡面的前恩名
assuming he's right
假設他是正確的
So everyone else went to compare with him to see the similarity
於是其他人都去跟他比較看相似度
Then if any of your voices follow the former name
那你如果哪一個聲音跟著前恩名
people are like
人民都像
That means he probably really has Obama.
那就表示他恐怕是真的有歐巴馬
you can give him extra points
就可以給他加分
Then I can reorder
然後我就可以重新排序
After getting a better result
得到一個比較好的結果之後
users can see
才可以使用者看
do so
這樣做的話
Mine is making considerable progress right now
我的馬上獲得相當的進步
because this is indeed
因為這個確實是
if they are all alike
如果都很像的話
I'm afraid he really has Obama.
他恐怕真的有歐巴馬了
Then there is one thing to say
那麼這裡面有一件事情要說一下
How is this similarity calculated?
這相似度怎麼算
The similarity of this sound is difficult to calculate
這個聲音的相似度是很難算的
Let's take an example
我們舉例來講
Suppose this is statement XI
假設這是語句XI
We feel like he has an Obama in him
我們覺得說他裡面好像有一個歐巴馬
But I opened the word map to see
不過我把詞圖打開來看
Not just one Obama, but several
歐巴馬不只一個有好幾個
I'll just pick the one with the highest score.
我就選擇裡面分數最高的那一條
Let's say this is Obama
假設這個是歐巴馬
So where is the relative feature item ranked?
那這個相對的這個特徵項量排在哪裡
This bunch of feature items
這一堆特徵項量
I'm assuming he's Obama
我就假設他是歐巴馬
So what?
那麼於是呢
another word from me
我另外一句話
kinda like having obama
有點像有歐巴馬
I'll just put that against Obama's bunch
我就把那個相對於歐巴馬的那一堆
Take out that part too
那一段也拿出來
so i want to make them
於是我要做他們
The two Obamas compare
這兩個歐巴馬來比
do they look like
他們像不像
this is the problem
這是問題來了
Because they are different in length
因為他們長短就不一樣
different lengths
長短不一樣
Obama inside is different
裡面的歐巴 馬亞都不一樣
how do i compare
我怎麼比呢
we need to make a
我們需要做一個
so-called dynamic time calibration
所謂的動態時間校準
What does it mean
這是什麼意思呢
if we look at
我們如果看一下
This picture probably understands
這張圖大概瞭解
These are the two Obamas
這是兩個歐巴馬
different length
長度就不一樣
The sound of the wave in this bar is also different.
這個巴裡面那個波的音也就不一樣
how do i compare
我怎麼比呢
I put an Obama on the horizontal axis
我把一個歐巴馬放在橫軸
In addition, Obama is on the heavy axis
另外歐巴馬放在重軸
If I draw the value of a certain parameter inside
我如果畫裡面的某一個參數的值
they have changes like this
他們有這樣子的變化
then you can imagine
那你馬上可以想像
It is said that this point should be compared with this point
照說是這一點要跟這一點來比
compare this with this
這一點要跟這一點來比
This is more like
這樣子才比較像
it means
這個意思是說
I want to be on this two-dimensional plane
我要在這個二維的平面上
find a curve
找一條曲線
That curve tells me who's up against whom
那條曲線告訴我誰跟誰比
right
才對
Because they are different in length
因為他們長短都不一樣了
Here is a schematic
這是一個示意圖
The more realistic picture is the first
比較真實的圖是第一
this one
這壹張
This is the horizontal axis, the vertical axis, the two Obamas
這是橫軸 縱軸 兩個歐巴馬
we understand that this is actually
我們了解這其實
This painting is actually a ten-spectrum
這個畫的其實就是個十頻譜
The vertical axis is the frequency
這個縱軸是頻率
this is the frequency
這個是頻率
then you can see that i am
那麼你可以看到我是
A quantity is compared with a quantity
一個項量跟一個項量在比
like this bunch of people said
像這一堆人表示
This item is at the same time as here
這一個項量同時跟這裡
A lot of items to compare and so on
好多個項量來比等等
then i will do this
那我要做這件事
After ten them well
把他們十還好了之後
Let's compare again
再來做比對
let me know my accuracy
讓我知道我的正確率
my similarity
我的相似度
Okay, this is a method just mentioned
好 這是剛才講的壹個方法
Let's think of another way
再來想 另外壹個方法
we just said i assume
我們剛才說我假設
In the search results, Qian Enming is correct
出搜結果裏面前恩明是正確的
It doesn't make sense
這話是不太通的
Why is Qian Enming right?
憑什麽前恩明是正確的呢
I think another way should be
我想 另外壹個辦法應該是
I put all the search results
我把全部的出搜結果
Take the similarity between the two
都拿來兩兩的相似度
to be used as a reference
來作為重判參考
how to do it
那怎麽做呢
Then we can put the search results inside
那我們可以把出搜結果裏面
every sentence
每壹句
Treat it as a node and turn it into a graph
當成一個節點 化成一張圖
Between points and points is the similarity between dramas
點跟點之間就是劇跟劇之間的相似度
as the score of their connection
作為他們連線的分數
So a higher score means they are more like
因此分數越高表示他們越像
So the higher the score, the more similar it is
於是分數越高表示越像的話
We can do it with this
我們就可以用這個來做了
For example, suppose the drama X1 is very similar to the two sentences of X2X3
舉例來講 假設X1這一劇跟X2X3這兩句很像
Because they have a strong connection
因為他們這連著很強的連線
that they look alike
表示他們很像
If X2X3 are high scores
如果X2X3都是高分的話
Then X1 should be extra points
那麼X1應該就要加分了
In the same way, if X1X2 are all low scores
同理 如果X1X2都是低分的話
Then X1 should be deducted points
那麼X1就應該要扣分了
that means
這個意思也就是說
After we let all fractions flow on the graph
我們讓所有的分數在圖上流動之後
let it converge
讓它收斂
This means that all similar sentences
這個意思是說 凡是很像的句子
Because their connection score is high
因為他們的連線分數高
they can reinforce each other
他們就可以互相的補強確認
This mutually reinforcing confirmation makes all changes
這個互相補強確認就讓所有的變化
Yes, errors are reduced a lot
是的錯誤減少很多
Then after confirming the reinforcement
那麼經過了補強確認之後
We then confirm the results based on reinforcement
我們再根據補強確認的結果
to remake the sequence
來重拍序
this time i am all sentences
這個時候我是所有的句子
together to reinforce each other
一起來互相補強的
So I'm not predestined
因此我不是靠前恩命的
if i do
我如果這樣做的話
Have my scores improved?
我分數有沒有進步
Immediately noticeable improvement
馬上有明顯的進步
This is the second example
這是第二個例子
give another example
再舉一個例子
It's in machine learning
就是用機器學習裡面的
so-called supporting imager
所謂的支撐想像機
We have learned about machine learning in recent years
我們了解機器學習是近年
very popular topic
非常熱門的題目
because machine learning
因為借助機器來學習
We can do a lot of things that we couldn't do in the past
我們可以得到很多過去不能做到的事
An example here is
這裡一個例子就是
so-called supporting imager
所謂的支撐想像機
support victim machine
support victim machine
or SVM
或者SVM
The basic idea is this
這個基本的想法是這樣
I'm still the same
我還是一樣
After the user enters a command Obama
使用者輸入一個指令歐巴馬之後
I get a bunch of voices that might be Obama's
我得到一堆聲音可能有歐巴馬的
But I don't show this to users
但是我這個不給使用者看
Because this is obviously wrong
因為這個顯然錯很多
then what should we do
那怎麼辦呢
I'll take this as my payout result
我就拿這個我的出收結果
Presupposition
假設前恩命
is right , as a right offense
是正確的,當成正確的犯例
In the end Eun Myung assumed he was wrong
最後恩明假設他是錯誤的
make a mistake
當成錯誤的犯例
Then, I'll build a
然後呢,我來建一個
so-called supporting camera
所謂的支撐相量機
right and wrong examples
把正確範例跟錯誤範例
to build one between them
來建一個他們之間
how to divide
該怎麼分的一個方法
After that, I take mine
那之後呢,我拿我的這個
What about the results of all the departures?
全部的出走結果呢
Throw it into this camera
丟到這個相量機裡面去
let him reorder
讓他來重排序
get good , better sort
得到好的,比較好的排序
The result is the result
結果做,這個結果才可以
users see
使用者看
Then here we have to explain a little bit
那這裡我們要稍微解釋一下
This SVM or support camera
這個SVM或者支撐相量機
what is
是什麼
What it means is
那它的意思其實就是
In phasor space there are two groups
在相量空間裡面有兩群
known phasor
已知的相量
assuming these are correct
假設這些是正確的
these are wrong
這些是錯誤的
I want to find a plane and divide them
我要找一個平面,把它們分割開
what about this plane
這平面該怎樣呢
you may be like this
你可能像這樣
it could be
也可能是這樣
you want to take
你想拿
seem
似乎
this is the best why
這個最好 為什麼
because if you look at it this way
因為你如果這樣子看的話
it has the largest interval
它的間隔最大
in other words
換句話說
if you look at this
你如果看這樣的話
it's a little too close
這邊太近了一點
Not very good
不是很好
if you look at it this way
你這樣看的話
it's a little too close
這邊太近了一點
It's not good to be too close
這邊太近也不是很好
That's when it's going to be like this
那就是要變成這樣的時候
They are separated by the largest
他們間隔最大
I'll just put the closest point here
我就把這個最近的點在這裡
this way for best results
這樣得到最好的結果
This is the so-called support think two doses
這就是所謂的支撐想兩劑
After you get this flat separation
當你得到這個平面的分隔之後
The new position phasor is thrown in
新的位置相量丟進來
just use this to separate
就用這個來分隔
see it and know it's right
看它就知道它是正確的
still wrong
還是錯誤的
Then I can actually use it
那我其實可以根據它
distance from this plane
跟這個平面的距離
can be reordered
就可以重新排序
Sort in this vertical direction
在這個垂直方向排序
i will know
我就會知道
Who is the most correct and so on
誰比較是最對的等等
of course
那當然
many times
有很多時候
There will be some exception errors
會有一些例外的錯誤
For example
舉例來講
These are correct Obama
這些都是正確的歐巴馬
but there is one more
但是還有一個
For example, he was talking about
譬如說他在講的是
The student who gave birth to Europe, how about his parents
生歐的學生 他的爸媽如何
So what about Ou's parents?
所以歐的爸媽怎樣
hey come in too
嘿 也進來了
Then it's a wrong exception
那這是一個錯誤的例外
There is also the correct exception running to the
同樣也有正確的例外跑到那去的
If you have to divide it like this, it will be too difficult.
你如果一定要這樣去分的話實在太難了
So we usually allow some exception errors
所以我們通常允許若干的例外的錯誤
So why can I
那因此呢 我可以
such planes cut them
這樣的平面 把它們切開
And these two are the exceptions to the error
而這兩個人就當成是錯誤的例外
etc.
等等
Of course, there are still many times, no matter how you do it.
那當然還有很多時候其實不管怎麼做呢
I'm actually having a hard time separating the two groups.
我其實這兩群很難分
How can it be difficult to tell them apart?
他們那個很難分怎麼辦呢
We figured out how to use some mathematical models
我們想辦法用一些數學模型
Convert it to a different or higher space
把它轉換到不同或者更高位的空間去
hope in that space
希望在那個空間裡面
they can be cut and so on
他們是切得開來的等等
Then these are the basic spirits of the phasor class
那這些就是直升相量級的基本的精神
After understanding that, let's go back and read what we just said.
了解了 那個之後我們回來看剛才講的
We just said, let's say he's looking for Obama
我們剛才說 假設他要找歐巴馬
Then the first time I found out, the results are these
那我第一次找到出收結果是這些
Then I don't show it to the user
那我不給使用者看
Because he has a lot of
因為他裡面湊很多
I just assume that the top N names are the correct examples
我就假設前N名是正確範例
The last N names are wrong examples
最後N名是錯誤範例
I just use this to go
我就用這個去
A bunch of wrong and right to build a support item measuring machine
這一堆錯誤的正確的去建一個支撐項量機
Then he told me where the real cutting plane is
那他告訴我真正的切割平面在哪裡
So I threw all the output results in
於是我把所有的出收結果丟進來
According to the vertical distance of this plane
根據這個平面的垂直的距離
to reorder
來重新排序
Only the output results are shown to the user
排出來的結果才給使用者看
what's the result
這個結果怎麼樣呢
Immediately there will be great progress, etc.
馬上有很大的進步等等
I think the above few examples show how we can do something like this
我想以上幾個例子說明我們如何做這樣的事
Of course some people want to say
當然也有人想說
if it is like this
如果是這樣的話
so can i just
那我是不是可以乾脆
Since your speech recognition errors are so many
既然你的語音辨識錯誤那麼多
I don't want to recognize
我就不要辨識了
because I can let the user directly use the
因為我可以讓使用者直接用
input voice command
入語音指令
Since your command is voice
既然你的指令是語音的
I just follow this audio file on the Internet
我就跟這個網路上的語音文件
Just go and compare with those
直接去跟那些比對就好了
Can I beat the signal?
我比訊號行不行呢
This is the greatest benefit that can be done
這是可以做的最大的好處
It's just that I forgot to identify
就是我省去了辨識
There is no such thing as misidentification.
也就沒有辨識錯誤這件事了
but it is difficult
但是卻是很難的
you know what we just said
你知道我們剛才說過
It's different if you don't reach those two
到不到那兩個到就是不一樣的
the same person said the same reason
那同一個人說同一個因
can be very different
都可能很不一樣
What's more, different people say the same sentence
更何況不同的人說同一句話
is quite different
是相當不同的
So it's very likely that you've been comparing for a long time
所以你比了半天很可能
not easy to match
不容易比得對
So so far
因此到目前為止
This is an important research direction
這是很重要的研究方向
However, due to the lack of identification
不過因為少了辨識
The correct total value to compare against
要比對的正確總值
So it's still pretty bad
所以還是比較差的
Let's take an example
我們舉例來講
The dynamic time calibration we just talked about
我們剛才講的這個動態時間校準
It's a very good way to compare
就是一個非常好的比對的辦法
This is the various sounds in the sound file
這是聲音文件裡面各種聲音
This is a phonetic designation such as
這是一個語音指定譬如說
He's looking for Obama
他要找歐巴馬
I'll take him
我就拿他來
so compare i need
這麼比對我需要
Two by two I go to find between them
兩兩我都去找他們之間
the curve that can be compared
可以比對的那一條曲線
Then go compare and so on
然後去比對等等
This calculation is very large
這個計算量是非常大的
In order to reduce this calculation
為了減少這個計算量
can also be done like this
也可以這樣子做
That is, I first put the voice in
就是我先把聲音裡面
The more similar parts are cut into sections
比較像的部分切成一段一段
that's almost one tone
那幾乎就是一個一個音
For example this could be O
譬如說這可能是O
this is 8
這個是8
This wave R
這個波R
This is Ma Mo R and so on
這是馬 摩R等等
if so
那如果這樣的話
I will compare it piece by piece
我就一段一段去比
can do like this
可以這樣子做
But what?
不過呢
This is much less computationally intensive
這個馬上計算量小很多
but
但是呢
I can't be more correct
我不見得會比較正確
Of course there is a better way
那當然還有一個更好的辦法
we feel today
我們今天覺得
At this stage it looks like the best way to do this is to
現階段看起來最好的辦法是
use the model
用模型
That is to say, in this audio file
也就是說是這個語音文件裡面
all voices
所有的聲音
I have built it into
我都把它建構成
The hidden Markov model we just talked about
我們剛才講的隱藏式馬可夫模型
The biggest advantage of becoming a model is that
變成模型最大好處就是
it has a lot of chance
它裡面有很多機率
So put every possible variation
所以把各種可能的變化
It's all in there
都收在裡面了
So why?
那因此呢
To deal with different people saying the same sentence
要處理不同的人說同一句話
What about the difference in the signal?
訊號不同的這件事呢
This model works better
這種模型的效果是比較好的
Therefore
因此呢
What if the user says I want to find Obama?
當使用者說我要找歐巴馬的話呢
This, this, using this voice signal
這個這個用這個語音的訊號
What about these models?
去針對這些模型去找呢
is more effective
是效果比較好的
This is how this series of ideas
這是這樣這一系列的想法
Another idea called concept comparison
再一個想法所謂的概念比對
What is concept comparison?
什麼叫概念比對呢
It means that if the user says that I want Obama
意思是說假設使用者說我要把歐巴馬
Of course the machine I hope he gives me all the sentences with Obama in them
當然機器我希望他給我所有的句子裡面有歐巴馬的
But there are some sentences in
但是還有一些句子裡面
Without the word Obama
沒有歐巴馬這三個字
He was talking about something from the White House.
他講的明明是美國白宮的什麼東西
I wish I could find it too
我希望我也要能夠找到
Because he's what I want
因為他其實也是我要的
this means it works
這個意思是通的
Just without the literal Obama
只是沒有這個字面的歐巴馬而已
In other words, we have the so-called literal comparison and conceptual comparison.
也就是說我們這裡面有所謂的字面比對跟概念比對
Literal comparison is easier
字面比對是比較容易
Just ask Obama
你就找歐巴馬就好了
Concept comparison seems to be much more difficult
概念比對好像難很多
Because you need to know the White House and Obama
因為你要知道美國白宮跟歐巴馬
Actually, they are two very common words.
其實是很通的兩個詞
That is to say, I want to find sentences related to meaning
也就是說我要找到與意相關的句子
Even if it doesn't include your directive
即使裡面沒有包括你的指令
There are many ways to do this
有很多方法來做這件事
Below I think two simple examples to illustrate
底下我覺得兩個簡單的例子來說明
what do they mean
他們什麼意思
first method
第一個方法
I'm trying to analyze the sentence inside
我是想辦法去分析句子裡面的
hidden semantics
潛藏的語意
this is what we call
這是我們所謂的
Latent Semantic Analysis
潛藏語意的分析
There are many ways of doing this
有很多方法做的這樣
is a simple example
是一個簡單的例子
so-called probabilistic analysis
所謂的機率式的分析
The so-called PLSA
所謂的PLSA
how to explain this
這個怎麼解釋呢
We use a very simple concept to think
我們用很簡單的觀念來想
Let's say it's a bunch of files
假設這是一大堆文件
Or a bunch of voice files would work too
或者一大堆語音文件也可以
Text files can also
文字文件也可以
if in terms of voice
如果就語音而言
a bunch of sentences
這一大堆的語句
there are many words in them
他們裡面都有很多詞
There are many words in each
每一個裡面都有很多詞
The computer really doesn't know which word
電腦的確是不知道哪個詞
what word does it have to do with
是跟哪個詞有什麼關係
or something
或者什麼
still don't know
還是不知道的
But a computer can do one thing
但是電腦可以做一件事
it can be found saying
它可以發現說
inside this pile of files
這堆文件裡面
always have these words
老是有這些詞
there are these words again
又老是有這些詞
So we can imagine
於是我們就可以想像
These documents and these words
這些文件跟這些詞
maybe talking about a
可能是在講某一個
the concept or theme
這個概念或者主題
These dictionaries are similar to this
這些文典跟這個類似
It should be another concept
應該是講另外一個概念
or another topic
或者另外一個主題
For example
舉例來講
if this was obama
如果這是歐巴馬
This is the economic policy of the United States
這是美國的經濟政策
this is the presidential election
這個是總統大選
this is probably a theme
這大概是某一個主題
if this is bin laden
如果這個是賓拉登
this is iran
這個是伊朗
this is baghdad
這是巴格達
it might be another thing
這可能是另外一件事
etc.
等等
If you think about it this way
如果這樣子來想的話
what we do here
我們這裡做的事情
In fact, it is assumed that there is a series of
其實就是假設存在一系列的
hidden theme or concept
潛藏主題或者概念
that's it
就是這些
Then we base the vocabulary on
然後我們根據詞彙在
in a different file
不同的文件中
Co-Occurrence Statistics
共同出現的統計資訊
to analyze what themes are
來分析他們是哪些主題
so i will know
因此我會知道
Obama and the White House
歐巴馬跟白宮
belong to the same subject
是屬於同一個主題的
so they are
所以他們是
I though this directive is Obama
我雖然這個指令是歐巴馬
I can also find those
我也可以找那些
stuff in the white house
美國白宮的東西
it's a concept
這是一個概念
that another way
那另外一種做法
This so-called instruction extension
這所謂的指令拓展
query expansion
query expansion
Let's use a simple example
我們用個簡單例子
keeps stating that he assumes the user enters Obama
一直在說明他假設使用者輸入歐巴馬
I made this instruction into a so-called instruction model
我把這個指令做成一個所謂的指令模型
It's nothing special. He's just an Obama.
其實沒什麽特別他就是一個歐巴馬
That's all the words only W2 the word Obama
那這是所有的詞只有W2這個歐巴馬這個詞
Yes probability is 1, everything else is 0
是機率是1別的都是0
Then I'll do the first search with this command
那我就用這個指令先做第一次搜尋
get my search results
得到我的出搜結果
I can't allow users to see the search results
那出搜結果我不可以使用者看
because there are many mistakes
因為裡面錯很多
Then I'll assume ex Eun Myung is right
那我就把前恩明假設是正確的
Count what words are used in them
把他們裡面再用些什麽詞統計出來
For example, there are Obamas here, there are Obamas here
譬如說這邊的歐巴馬這邊都有歐巴馬
But here's the White House, he also has the White House
但是這邊的白宮他也有白宮
That means the White House should be what you want too.
那表示白宮應該也是你要的
So I use this to make a new instruction model
於是我就用這個可以做個新的指令模型
just add the white house
就把白宮加進來
But in turn, there's bin Laden over here.
但是反過來這邊有個賓拉登
no bin laden here
這邊沒有賓拉登
bin laden better not
賓拉登最好還是不要吧
Wait so I can create a new command
等等這樣我可以建一個新的指令
It is a lot more than the original instruction
它是把原来指令多了很多
just expanded
就是扩展了
I'll find it again with this command
我用这个指令再找一次
I only show users what I find out
找出来的东西我才给使用者看
This is the so-called instruction extension
这是所谓的指令扩展
Another big problem is
再一点很大的一个问题就是
Even if we use Google to find text files today
我们今天即使是用Google找文字文件
We also know that it is helpful for users to interact with the system
我们也知道使用者跟系统互动是很有帮助的
So for example, if you enter who
那么譬如说你输入什么人
After he showed me a bunch of stuff
他给我看一堆东西之后
let me click what to wait
我来点选什么等等
This interaction is very important
这互动是非常重要的
But with English or multimedia content
可是与英或者多媒体的内容
The biggest problem is that it's not easy to render on the screen
最大的问题是它不容易呈现在萤幕上
So it's not as clear as text
所以不像文字那样可以一目了然
is not easy to choose
是不容易点选的
I can't listen to every one of them
我不能每一个每个都去听
After listening to it, I found that it wasn't what I wanted.
听了之后发现都不是我要的
In this way, the user writes that the machine must be thrown away
这样使用者写定要把机器丢掉
So how do we make it easy for users to
那么因此我们如何让使用者可以方便的
Browse click
浏览点选
like text
像文字那样
this is a big problem
这是一个很大的问题
I found a lot of things and don't know what to do
我找了一大堆东西不想怎么办
how to do this
如何做这件事情呢
We are thinking of the following methods
我们想的是以下这些方法
what about the first one
第一个呢
I think of a way to replace the digital content of these voices only
我想办法仅可能替这些语音的数位内容
Build some language sessions of its keywords, etc.
建一些它的关键词等等的语会
Then create its title, create its summary
然后建它的标题 建它的摘要
Then what
然后呢
I try to build some knowledge structure
我想办法建一些知识结构
let me help me click to browse
让我帮助我点选浏览
has a nice user interface
有一个好的使用者介面
Then what
然后呢
I allow users to talk to my system
我让使用者可以跟我的系统对话
I'm going to say these things quickly
我底下很快说一下这些事情
For example
举例来讲呢
for example
比如说
First
第一个
We say that in this audio file
我们说这个语音文件里面
We hope to catch some key
我们希望抓一些关键
Key words or key phrases
关键词或者关键片语
There are only two
就两种了
a word is called a keyword
一个词叫做关键词
Otherwise, multiple words are called key phrases
否则好多个词叫做关键片语
Then we need to find these things out
那我们要找这些东西出来
The first question is that the key phrase has several words
那第一个问题就是关键片语是有好几个词
How do I know which words together form a key phrase?
我怎么知道哪几个词连起来是个关键片语呢
For example
舉個例子來講
President Barack Obama
美國總統歐巴馬
This is an obvious key phrase
這是一個很明顯的一個關鍵片語
How do I know it should be a key phrase?
我怎麽知道他應該是個關鍵片語呢
for example
舉例來說
If I found in my data
如果我在我的data裏面發現
the right side of america is often followed by the same word
美國的右邊經常跟著相同的詞
the word is called president
這個詞叫做總統
American presidents are often followed by the same word to the right
美國總統的右邊經常跟著相同的詞
that word is called obama
那個詞叫做歐巴馬
But President Obama's right
但是美國總統歐巴馬的右邊
followed by many different words
就跟著很多不同的詞了
that means
那就表示
This should be the right border of a phrase
這個應該是一個片語的右邊界
Similarly I can also find
同理我也可以發現
This is the left boundary of a phrase
這個是一個片語的左邊界
because there are many
因為這邊有很多
so I can use various statistics for each context
因此我可以根據每一個前後文的各種統計資訊
to figure out its boundaries
來算出它的邊界來
Knowing the boundaries doesn't mean he must be the key phrase
知道邊界不表示他一定是關鍵片語
So we still need a lot of other knowledge to confirm him
因此我們還要有很多別的知識來確認他
For example
舉例來講
The first confirmation is a mistake
第一個確認的就是一揚頓錯
Everyone knows
各位知道
when the speaker says key words
當說話的人說到關鍵詞
or key phrases
或者關鍵片語的時候
it often speaks a little slower
它常常語速會慢一點
the volume will be higher
音量會高一點
The change in pitch will be a little bigger
音高的變化會大一點
That's the obvious message to me
這就是明顯的訊息告訴我
it is the keyword
它是關鍵詞
again the word itself
再來這個詞本身
we could have just said
我們可以剛才已經說過
We can analyze its underlying themes
我們可以分析它的潛藏的主題
or concept
或者概念
I can based on its theme
我可以根據它的主題
or concept to know
或者概念來知道
Is it a keyword
它是不是一個關鍵詞
For example
舉例來講
the word obama
歐巴馬這個詞
possibly in two themes
可能在兩個主題裡面
high probability
幾率都很高
This is the US presidential election
這個是美國總統的大選
This is America
這個是美國區
West Season Bin Laden
西季 賓拉登
Both of these are highly likely
這兩個它幾率都很高
Other chances are very low
其他幾率都很低
Let's say this is the Oscars
譬如說這個是奧斯卡金像獎
This is a baseball game in Taiwan
這個是台灣的棒球比賽
None of them have Obama
他們都沒有歐巴馬的
This looks like a keyword
這個看起來就像個關鍵詞
why keywords
為什麼關鍵詞
Usually only concentrated in
通常只集中出現在
A handful of conceptual themes inside
少數的概念主題裡面
This is for example a
這個譬如說是一個
today or morning
今天或者早上
or very
或者是非常
This kind of word appears in almost every topic
这种词出现在每一个主题里面都差不多多
That means it's probably not a keyword, and so on.
那就表示它大概不是关键语会等等
Of course there are other important knowledge
当然还有别的很重要的知识
For example, the frequency of occurrence of the word
譬如说这个词出现的频率啦
its part of speech etc.
它的词类啦等等
it's all about
这个都是有关的
What I just talked about is how to extract keywords
刚才讲的是如何抽关键词
Let's talk about how to do file extraction
再来我们说如何做文件摘药
These will be shown to you in actual combat later.
这些待会儿都会给各位看到实战的东西
Then the voice file we hope to be able to extract
那么语音文件我们是希望能够抽
Automatically draw a pill
自动抽个摘药
How to draw it? For example, this is a voice file
怎么抽呢?举例来讲这是一个语音文件
There are six sentences in it
里面有六句话
A circle in each sentence means a word
每一句里面的一个圆圈表示是一个词
This blue one means correct identification
这个蓝色的表示正确辨识
Red indicates identification error
红色表示辨识错误
if i have a way to find out in there
如果我有办法在里面找出
two particularly important sentences
两句特别重要的句子
wrap it up
把它兜起来
as medicine
作为摘药
What if I treat it as after taking the medicine?
那如果我当它是摘药之后呢
It can be played back with its original sound
可以把它用它的原来的声音播放出来
As long as it is the original sound played out
那只要它是原来声音播放出来
it's the wrong question
是錯誤的問題了
it all sounds right
聽起來都是對的了
What about this?
那這樣呢
is what we call this sound
是我們所謂的這個聲
voice summary
語音摘要
So of course the question is how to choose the drama
那麼當然問題是怎麼選劇了
There are several basic principles in the selection of plays
選劇有幾個基本的原則
for example
譬如說
Anything that contains more
凡是包含更多
more important word
越重要的詞
or words that look more like keywords
或者越像是關鍵詞的詞
it's more important
它越重要
it contains
它所包含
Because I can analyze concepts now
因為我現在可以分析概念嘛
So if it contains the concept
所以如果它所包含的概念
Closer to the concept of the full text
跟全文的概念比較接近的
that should be more important
那應該是越是重要的
In addition
另外呢
What if a sentence has been selected?
已經選出一個句子的話呢
It concept should be next sentence to avoid repetition
它概念應該下一句要避免重複
etc.
等等
Then I can build my
那這樣我就可以建立出我的
audio summary
語音的摘要來
I can show you this later
這個待會兒可以給各位看到
example
例子
come again
再來呢
I also wish to generate headers
我也希望產生標題
Because the title is easier to click
因為標題比較容易點選
what about the title
那標題怎麼做呢
you know
你知道呢
The characteristic of this title is
這個標題的特色就是
it is text
它是文字
it should be shorter
它要短
but to read
但是要刻讀
Let me give you an example here
那我這邊舉一個例子
The basic way we do headlines
我們做標題的基本的方法
is the voice file
就是語音文件進入
I first identify
我先辨识
then make a summary
然后做出摘要
i by the words inside the abstract
我由摘要里面的词
Then choose the important words in it
然后来选里面重要词
make a title
做标题
There are optional words
这里面有选词
model with word choice
有选词的模型
how to sort words
词怎么排序
sorted model
有排序的模型
How long should the title have it's model etc
标题应该多长有它的模型等等
These models use training corpus
这些模型都是用训练语料
trained
训练出来的
What's the meaning
什么意思
Because I can catch a lot of words written by people on the Internet
因为我可以上网抓一大堆人写的文字
with title in it
里面有标题的
someone made the title
有人做的标题的
The text I can write about the candidate
我可以就人选的写的文字
Make headlines with people to train those in the middle
跟人做标题去训练中间的这些
how to choose words
如何选词
how to sort
如何排序
how does it determine its length etc.
它如何定它的长度等等
so I can use this to make the title
因此我可以用这个做出标题来
This meeting will also show you the real thing
这个待会也会给各位看到真实的东西
come again
再来呢
knowledge structure
知识结构
what is knowledge structure
什么叫知识结构
we don't know
我们其实不知道
But let's give two examples
不过我们举两个例子
The first example is that we put any
第一个例子就是我们把凡是
concept or theme
概念或主题
Subdivide the concept or theme of the audio file
把语音文件的概念或主题分裙
and then arrange it into a two-dimensional vertical structure
然后把它排成二维的竖状结构
For example, if the concept theme is very similar, turn it into a group of
舉例來講 凡是這個概念主題很像的把它變成一群
Put a piece inside the two
放在二位裡面的一塊
I tag it with a set of keywords
我用一組關鍵詞來標它
Let the user know what it is at a glance
讓使用者一看就知道它是什麼
And then, if there are many uniform groups
然後呢 統一群如果很多的話
I can go down one more layer and expand and divide into groups and so on.
我可以再下一層 再展開 再分成好幾群等等
I will show you an example of this later
這個待會兒也會給各位看到例子
What's more, I can also make a picture of keywords
再來呢 就是 我也可以做成關鍵詞的圖
For example, if I find a bunch of voice files
舉例來講 我如果找到一堆語音文件
I find the keywords for each voice file
我為每一個語音文件找出它的關鍵詞
Mark it with these key words to mark what it is
標出來 用這些關鍵詞來標它是什麼東西
Then what about the relationship between these keywords?
然後呢 這關鍵詞之間的關係呢
I can draw a picture to show how they are related
我可以畫一個圖 說它們是什麼關係
This helped me find
這個幫助我去找
I will show you an example of this later
這個待會兒也會給各位看到例子
One last thing to say
最後要說一下
There is one more dialogue, how to do the dialogue?
還有一個要對話 對話怎麼做呢
Just assume that the user enters a command
只是这样假设说使用者输入一个指令
Also looking for the President of the United States
还要找美国总统
Then the machine went to find it
那么机器就去找了一下
As a result, what the President of the United States did
结果美国总统他做的事情
a lot of weird
奇奇怪怪很多
very scattered
非常零散
so that the result is so bad
以至于这个结果太差
The machine knows it's not working
机器一看就知道这个是不行的
If this large pile is handed over to the user
如果这一大堆交给使用者的话
Users are annoyed
使用者一看就烦死了
So we don't provide this result to the user
所以我们就不把这个结果提供给使用者
Ask the user to say if you can add one more command
要求使用者说你能不能再多加一个指令
so the user
于是使用者
what i want is diplomacy
我要的是外交
After having this, the machine will look different again
有了这个之后机器再找就不一样了
He found a lot of things about the president of the United States related to diplomacy
他找到很多美国总统跟外交有关的事
However, there is a trend
不过发现里面有一个趋势
That is, many of them are related to the Middle East.
就是很多都是跟中东有关的
Middle East is their keyword
中东是他们的关键词
Since this is the case
既然是这样的话
but still messy
可是还是很乱
At this time, the machine can use this keyword
这个时候机器可以用这个关键词
Go to confirm with the user that what you want is the Middle East
去跟使用者确认说你要的是中东
If this is the user says yes
如果这个是使用者说是
right
对
then i can throw all the middle east to it
那我就可以把所有的中東的丟給它
Then probably won't die
那大概就不離世了
Or the user says no, what I want is Asia
或者使用者說不是啊 我要的是亞洲啊
That's okay, I already know it's Asia.
那也可以 那已經知道是亞洲了
I can search again and find Asia and so on
我就可以再找一次 把亞洲找出來等等
this is called a dialogue
這是所謂的對話
Okay, so I've said everything on the picture just now.
好 這樣我把剛才這個圖上的東西都說了
Here is a summary of the key vocabulary title Knowledge Structure Dialogue
這邊是關鍵語彙標題摘要 知識結構 對話
Alright, most of what I'm going to say today ends here.
好 那今天要說的大部分到這裡告一個段落
The last paragraph below is to show you some live demonstrations
底下最後一段就是給各位看一些現場展示的部分
We are divided into three levels
我們分成三個層次
a general structure
一個是一般結構
one is general knowledge
一個是一般知識
one is professional knowledge
一個是專業性知識
one is language learning
一個是語言學習
Let's look at the first general knowledge part first
那我們先看第一個一般性知識的部分
What we show you is official news
我們給各位看的是公式新聞
same ok
一樣 OK
No, is your system turned on?
不 你那個系統打開了沒有
turn on the system first
先把系統打開
The formula news on our side is from 2002 to 2003
我們這邊的公式新聞是在2002年到2003年
A total of about 1100 pieces were recorded
總共錄了大概1100則
sorry 6000
抱歉 6000則
News with a formula of about 110 hours
以大概110小時的公式新聞
make a news system
做成一個這個新聞系統
It was done in the spring of 2006
當時這是在2006年的春天完成的
So it's an old system from 7 years ago
所以是7年前的老系統了
We didn't put it online at the time
當時我們沒有把它放在網路上
only in one machine
只做在一台機器裡面
So we still bring that machine to repair today for everyone to see
所以我們今天還是帶那台機器來修給大家看
So it's a comparison
所以是比較
OK
OK
minimize it first
先把它minimize
OK good
OK 好
OK, let's take a look now
好 那我們現在先來看一下
what i'm going to say now is this is this
我現在要說的是 這個是 這個
first general knowledge
第一個一般性的知識
Our example is TV news
我們舉例就是電視新聞
So let's think about what TV news is like
那麼我們想一想電視新聞是怎樣的
basically it probably contains no text
基本上它大概不含文字
Then its themes are very diverse
然後它的主題是很多元的
So the group title we just said
所以我們剛才說的分群標題
Keywords are helpful for browsing
關鍵詞都是有助於瀏覽的
it's not easy to recognize
它不太容易辨識
Because there are so many new words
因為新詞特別多
But for most news
但是對多數新聞而言
Most users don't need to know that detailed
多數使用者不必要知道那麼詳細
So cheating on the title is helpful
所以詐要跟標題是有幫助的
The information of each news itself is complete
每一則新聞本身資訊是完整的
Listen to news without additional information
聽新聞不需要額外資訊
So the purpose of the knowledge structure is to assist browsing
所以知識結構的目的是協助瀏覽用的
Okay, let's look at the part just now
好 那我們先來看剛才的部分
Let's show you a TV news first
我們先給各位看一則電視新聞
you can find out
你可以瞭解一下
The voice signal of this formula news is below
這一則公式新聞的語音訊號在底下
You see the full length is more than 1 minute and 40 seconds
你看到全長是1分40多秒
Then we have this in sync
那麼我們同步的有這個
The picture is also drawn here
画面也画在这里
We can listen once to know what it's talking about
我们可以听一次知道它在讲什么
Southwest Airlines has a Boeing 737
西南航空有一架波音737
When flying from Baltimore to Chicago
从霸尔地摩飞到芝加哥的时候
On landing in a blizzard
在降落时遇上了暴风雪
overshot the runway and the airport fence
冲出了跑道和机场围墙
It hit two cars on the road
结果撞上了马路上的两部汽车
At that time, after the chicken blood was beaten to 18 centimeters
当时鸡血打18公分后
Is the plane under surveillance because it ran too slippery?
这架飞机是否因为跑到太滑而照视
Authorities are still investigating
有关当局还要调查
Chicago Airport 33 years ago
33年前芝加哥机场
There has also been a major crash
也曾发生一起重大的坠击以外
are all in the result radio
都是在结果 radio
Kashiba GG
香芝GG
I can speed up
我可以加速了
but can follow the master tape
但可以按照母带
this three-letter sound
这个三字声音
no translation
一語不译
then we are not good
那我们不利
as long as we are
我们只要本来就是
understand that is a
了解那那是一个
only a few places
只有好几个地方
1 times the word today Haven
今天1倍字 Haven
Already counted
已经的数了
I see this Tongiting La Viet
我对此看得 Tongiting 拉越
Runway and airport fence results
跑道和机场围墙结果
Collide
撞
put two cars on the road
放上了馬路上的兩部汽車
One dead, eleven wounded
造成一個人死亡 十一人受傷
Chicago International Airport in the midst of an out-of-air accident
芝加哥國際機場在空外意外發生時
still snowing
仍然大雪分飛
Fire trucks and ambulances rushed to the scene immediately
消防車跟救護車立刻趕到現場進行救援
But the university keeps going
不過大學下個不停
It also increases the difficulty of rescue
也增加了救援的困難度
The accident happened at local time
這起意外發生在當地時間
7:15pm on the 8th
8號晚間7點15分
Southwest Airlines had 103 passengers on board
西南航空這家在有103名乘客
Active Crew Boeing Air Fan Airliner
積極組員的波音氣扇器客機
Flying from Baltimore to Chicago Airport
從巴爾迪摩飛底芝加哥機場時
Suspected because of bad weather
疑似因為天后不佳
Winning off the runway and forming a strong knot
不勝衝出跑道結為強
Hit two cars on the road
撞上馬路上的兩部汽車
One of them got stuck under the plane
其中一部卡在飛機下方
6-year-old boy dies in car
造成車上一名6歲男童死亡
Eleven people on board and on the ground were injured
機上與地面總共十一人受傷
The plane itself was also involved in the collision
飛機本身也因為衝撞
Damaged the nose and dropped a Secret
造成機頭受損及一具隱情掉落
Eyewitnesses described the situation
目擊者描述了當時的情境
The airport staff pointed out that when the snow reached 18 centimeters,
機場人員指出 當時機雪達18公分後
Did this plane create momentum because it flew to Taihua?
這架飛機是否因為跑到太華而造勢
Authorities are still investigating
有關當局還要調查
33 years ago, there was one at the Chicago airport.
33年前 芝加哥機場也曾發生一起
major crash accident
重大的墜擊意外
45 people left
當時有45人離難
On this plane, airport personnel at the time noted that
在這架飛機上 當時的機場人員指出
The airport staff at the time pointed out that
當時的機場人員指出
45 people left
當時有45人離難
Fruit News This Meeting Variation
果實新聞 這會面變異
This is more than 1 minute and 40 seconds of news
這是1分40多秒的新聞
Everyone, just saw
各位 剛才已經看到
let's see again
我們再看一次
How did we extract the summary?
我們摘要是怎麼摘的呢
Just find these two sentences in it
就是在裡面找到這兩句
this red sentence
這紅色的這一句
with this red line
跟這紅色的這一句
These two sentences are the most important sentences
這兩句是最重要的句子
wrap it up
把它兜起來
Almost the most important part of the full text
幾乎就是全文裡面最重要的部分
we call it a summary
我們把它稱為摘要
These two add up to 19 seconds
這兩個加起來是19秒
What about the picture?
畫面呢
we need another team
我們請另外一個團隊
Help us draw important pictures
幫我們抽重要的畫面
It is based on the message of the screen
它是根據畫面的訊息
For example, someone's face is moving
譬如說有人臉在動的
changed face
換了一張臉的
or this thing that's moving
或者是這個有東西在動的什麼
is the important thing
就是重要的東西
They also add up to 19 seconds in this way
他們這樣也湊成19秒
So get a 19 second pick
因此得到一個19秒的摘藥
let's see it again now
我們現在再看一次
Southwest Airlines has a Boeing 737
西南航空有一架波音737
When flying from Faltimore to Chicago
從法爾地摩飛到芝加哥的時候
blizzard on landing
在降落時遇上的暴風雪
overshot the runway and the airport fence
衝出了跑道和機場圍牆
It hit two cars on the road
結果撞上了馬路上的兩部汽車
When the snow reached 18 centimeters
當時機雪達18公分後
Is this plane making a fuss about being too slippery?
這架飛機是否因為跑到太滑而造勢
Authorities are still investigating
有關當局還要調查
Chicago Airport 33 years ago
33年前芝加哥機場
There was also a major crash
也曾發生一起重大的墜擊意外
you can see
各位可以看到
last sentence
最後這句話
It is different from the previous sentence
是跟前面這句比較不一樣的
There are a lot of things in this
這中間講的很多東西
In fact, the previous sentence already exists
其實前面這句已經有了
so no more
所以就都不要了
etc.
等等
This is already taken
這個是已經摘藥
we just said
我們剛才說
Actually, I can make the title
其實我可以做標題是可以的
Let's show you below
我們底下給各位看
This is a title made by a computer
這是電腦做的標題
then you can initiate
那你可以發起
Whether it is the title or the abstract of this computer
這個電腦的標題也好 摘要也好
Of course no one does it well
當然沒有人做得好
this man must do better
這個人一定做得更好
But our point is not that he wants to compare with others
但是我們的point並不是說他要跟人比
but after having these things
而是在於有了這些東西之後
can help us browse
可以幫助我們瀏覽
Then sometimes I don't have to listen to the end
那麼有的時候我可以不用再聽完
And I saw his title
而我一看他的標題
listen to his abstract
一聽他的摘要
I know that, do I still want to listen?
我就知道那個我還要不要聽
I really want to hear me go play the full thing
我真的要聽我去播放完整的東西
on the line
就行了
You may think
那各位可能覺得說
You may have picked the best sentence for this one.
你這個可能是選了一句做得最好的
come to this show
來這一秀
that's not true
那其實不然
I just said that our system
我剛才說過我們這個系統
What's inside is
裡面收的是
PTV News in 2002 to 2003
公視新聞在2002到2003年
a total of one hundred and ten hours
總共一百一十小時
One hundred and ten hours six thousand
一百一十小時六千則
Every news does what it just did
每一則新聞都做了剛才的事
Then make a system like this
那麼變做成一個這樣的系統
That
那
Katamin Ecstasy
Katamin 搖頭丸
or mahiro
或者是大馬海洛
Suoying, various types of bottles, Department of Health today
鎖英 多瓶種類 五花八門 衛生署今天
This is the news we usually see when we go home and turn on the TV
這個是我們通常回到家裡打開電視所看到的新聞
Then I don't want to hear 80% of the news he tells.
那麼八成他講的新聞我都不想聽
But turning around, there's nothing I want to hear
可是轉來轉去就是沒有我要聽的
So we want a formula like this
因此我們就想一個這樣子的公式
such a news system
這樣的一個新聞系統
The first one I put all received news
第一個我把所有收到的新聞
made his abstract and title respectively
分別都做了他的摘要跟標題
Abstract here Title here
摘要在這裡 標題在這裡
Then I divide all the news into these six categories
然後我把所有的新聞分成這六大類
International Politics, Finance, etc.
國際政治財經等等
According to his content, it's all made by machines
根據他的內容 這都是機器做的
Then my homepage is the one for each type of news
然後我的首頁就是每一類新聞的
The most recent one is presented with his title
最近的那一則 以他的標題來呈現
Users can see if I want
使用者可以看看我要不要
If you want, click him to get the complete news
要的話點選他就得到完整的新聞
Click on the summary and I will hear the summary
點選摘要我就聽到摘要
Of course, this, this, each of these may be
那當然了 這個可能這個每一則都
not what i want to see
不是我要看的
then i can choose
那我可以選
Let's say I just want to watch international news
譬如說我要光看國際新聞
Well there's a whole lot of international news here
那這裡有一大堆國際新聞
Then I can watch political news, financial news, etc.
那我可以看政治新聞 財經新聞等等
even if that's the case
那即使是這樣的話呢
There may be more international news
這國際新聞可能還很多啊
you see so much international news
你看到國際新聞這麼多
Still hard to choose
還是很難點選啊
What should we do then?
那這時候怎麼辦呢
I can click on this bird to see the picture
我可以點這個鳥看圖
The picture of this bird is what we just saw
這個鳥看圖就我們剛才看到
is my analysis of news according to the vocabulary of its content
就是我把新聞根據它的內容的詞彙的分析
I will divide it into nine categories
我就把它分成九大類
Of course each category is
當然每一類是什麼
computer doesn't know
電腦是不知道的
but what about each category
但是每一類呢
i can smoke it keywords
我可以抽它的關鍵詞
or key phrase
或者關鍵片語
after pulling out
抽出來之後
make it the most important keyword
把它最重要的關鍵詞
The highest score is listed here
分數最高的列在這裡
Let's see
那我們人來看
You can probably see what it is
大概就看得出來它是什麼了
For example
譬如說呢
what is this
這個是什麼
There were planes, explosions, and earthquakes
又有飛機又爆炸又有地震
It's all kinds of natural and man-made disasters
這是各種天災人禍
what is this
這是什麼呢
Another Ministry of Health, another whale, another case
又是衛生部又是鯨鳥又是病例
I know this should be a health problem for the whole world
就知道這個應該是全世界的健康問題
with disease
跟疾病問題
This is a chair-tooth dispute in the Middle East
這個是中東的椅牙糾紛
This is North and South Korea and so on
這是南北韓等等
It can be seen that the Overseas Bridge is full, etc.
這都看得出來海外橋 包滿等等
That's a little weird
就這個有點奇奇怪怪
like nothing
好像什麼都不是
We later found out that this is
後來我們了解的這個其實就是
none of above
以上皆非
In other words, all the news we had at the time
也就是說我們當時所有新聞裡面
It can be roughly divided into these eight categories
大概可以分成這八大類
There is a category that is really nothing
就是有一類實在什麼都不是的
called none of the above
叫做以上皆非
Let's say I want to watch all kinds of natural and man-made disasters
假設我想看這個各種天災人禍
I can go in from here
我可以從這點進去
i get the next layer
我就得到下一層
We just saw two-dimensional structures
我們剛才看到二維的結構
This layer expands it to nine
這一層把它展開又是九個
This natural and man-made disaster can be divided into
這個天災人禍可以分成
Let's say it's a homicide
譬如說這是凶殺案的
this is the plane that crashed
這是飛機墜機的
volcanic earthquake tsunami
火山地震海嘯的
you say it's weird
你說很奇怪
Why do tsunamis and volcanoes go together
為什麼海嘯跟火山會在一起
because they use similar words
因為它們用的詞很像
For example, this hurricane will be with heavy snow
譬如說這個颶風會跟大雪在一起
It is also a similar relationship between the words used
也是用的詞很像的關係
may not find
不一定會發現
This strike is also a disaster
這個罷工也是一種災害
because he used words like
因為他用的詞是像的
For example, road section or traffic impassability
譬如說路段或者說是交通不通了什麼
So the word used is like
所以是用的詞是像的
How do you say this teenager is also
你說這個青少年怎麼也是
because he was a riot and so on
因為他是暴動等等
So if you want to know about this teenager's disaster
那你如果想知道這個青少年的這個災
Scourge or something
的天災人或是什麼
you click in to see
你點進去看
that's what he's talking about
他就是在講這些
then we can
那我們可以
Because I only have two layers in total now
因為我現在總共只有兩層
In fact, this can be many layers
其實這個是可以很多層
But now because there is not much news about this
不過現在因為這個新聞不多
So a total of two layers
所以總共兩層
So by now it's bottom
所以到這時候已經是底了
all of his
那他的所有的
There are many more news like that listed here
像那新聞列在這裡還很多
etc.
等等
Then we can see for example
那我們可以看看譬如說
what is this one about
這一則講的是什麼
I can click in and have a look
我可以點進去看一下
12 days of riots in France
持續了12天的法國暴動
On the evening of the 7th in Paris and Toulouse
7號晚間在巴黎以及土魯斯等地
Become again
又成
You probably know what he's talking about
你大概知道他在講的就是這件事
The title is sometimes weird
這個標題有的時候怪怪的
but you probably know what he's talking about
不過你大概了解他在講什麼
This is another one, let's click in and have a look
這是另外一則我們點進去看一下
The violent riots continued, and the sudden golden boy set fire on the street in the early morning of the 14th
發火暴動持續 突如斯的金少年14號 清晨在街頭放火
Wait, this browsing we call Top Down
等等 這個我們稱為Top Down的瀏覽
because you're looking down from the top of the tree
因為你是從樹頂端向下看的
Of course, I can do it the other way around.
當然其實我也可以反過來
Battle Nights Looking Up from the Bottom
Battle Nights從底下向上看
If I go back to the main screen
我如果回到主畫面去
Let's say I'm here looking for international news
假設我是在這裡找國際新聞
I look down from here
我從這往下看
Suppose I see a certain news
假設我看到某一則新聞
For example, the Iraqi election bombing, I want to see this one
譬如說伊拉克大選 爆炸 我要看這一則
I'll just click in and see
我就點進去看
Eight big polling places just opened their doors
八個大的投票所才剛敞開大門
let voters vote
讓選民進行投票
There was a loud bang in the green zone
綠區就轟然一聲傳出巨大的
Suppose I see this one, when I finish this one,
假設我看到這一則 看完這一則的時候
I feel like I want to know more news
我覺得我想知道更多的新聞
I can click related news
我就可以點相關新聞
related news
相關新聞一點之後
It took me to that spot in its tree
它就把我帶到它的樹裡面的那個位置去了
just here
就是剛才在這裡
These are all about the Iraqi bombings, right?
這些就是都是跟伊拉克爆炸是嗎
related news
有關的新聞
then i can do more
那我可以多
I listen to the news here
我聽這邊的新聞
I can also go up one level
我也可以向上一層去
just get
就得到
i am here now
我現在是在這裡
It's eight brains exploding and so on.
就是八個大腦爆炸等等
that belongs to this block
那在屬於這一塊裡面
I'm on the upper floor
我在上一層
I will go back to the part of natural disaster characters and wait.
會回到天災人物的這一塊裡面去等等
This is where the guaranteed bottom-up search
這就是保證到從下而上的搜尋
of course
那當然
I can actually find something else
我其實還可以想找別的東西
For example
舉例來講
If I go back to the main screen
我如果回到主畫面之後
I can actually do the search directly
我其實是可以直接做搜尋的
In our case it is called retrieval
我們這邊稱為檢索
let's try
我們來試試看
is it possible
是不是可以
ok
ok
good
好
let's try
我們來試看看
I will retest
我來重測
try mute
試一下靜音
Okay, now I should be able to go in with my voice.
好 現在我應該聲音是可以進去了
so what
所以呢
try again
再試一次
then let's try
那麼 我們來試看看
Please help me find the White House
請幫我找美國白宮
It doesn't seem to go in. Let's do it again.
好像沒進去 我們再來一次
good
好
I want him not working now
我要 他現在不 work
Please help me find the White House
請幫我找美國白宮
He changed the environment, it seems
他換了一個環境 好像
is such a relationship
是這樣的關係
OK, let's try again, that's right.
OK 好 我們再試一次 對了 這個才對
ok ok one more time
OK 好 再來一次
OK, please help me find the White House
好 請幫我找美國白宮
No, still not
不對 還是沒有啊
Should be a little better. Let's do it again.
應該差得穩一點 我們再來一次
Please help me find the White House
請幫我找美國白宮
Got it, got it, OK
有了 有了 OK
According to the New York Times report
對於《紐約時報》的報導指出
Senior U.S. intelligence agent from Itain, Iran
美國高級情報人員從伊泰伊朗
Emergencies of practice in computer
實踐的緊急性電腦中
Discover more than 1000 pages of computer patterns
發現1000多頁電腦模式
Strong selling shopping channel no matter what
強力出銷的購物頻道 不論什麼樣
well what we just saw
好 我們剛才看到的
it moved
它動掉了
this
這個
ok i think u can make this
OK 我想 影言你可以使這個
This is what I just said was completed in 2006, 7 years ago
這個是 我剛才講這個是在2006年完成的7年前了
So inevitably I'm talking now and he's going in
所以難免 我現在不斷地說話 他不斷地進去
so he keeps finding something else
所以他不斷地找到別的東西
he found something different now
他現在找到不同的東西了
OK, what about our part?
好 那我們這一部分呢
we'll stop here
我們就秀到這裡
Let's go back to the main screen
我們回到主畫面去
Then I leave here too
然後我在這裡也離開
Okay, I was talking about the TV news.
好 剛才說的是電視新聞
Let's look at the second one, which is professional knowledge
我們看第二個 就是專業性的知識
What about specialized knowledge? A good example
專業性的知識呢 一個很好的例子
online course
就是網路課程
What about online courses, you can download
網路課程呢 你可以下載
Imagine that there are so many online courses today
想像到今天有非常多的網路課程
But you often take a long time
但是你常常需要很長的時間
in order to fully learn
才能完整學習
For example, a 45-hour essay class
譬如說45小時一文課
It is difficult for a busy person to listen carefully for 45 hours
很忙的人是很難去認真聽45小時的
so what can we do
所以我們有什麼辦法呢
real online courses
確實有的網路課程
is searchable by a browser
是有瀏覽器可以搜尋的
for example
譬如說
which one are you looking for
你要找哪一個
just go find that part, you can find it
就去找到那一段是找得到的
the problem is to say
問題是說
The course is structured
課程之時是有結構的
You learn the former to understand the latter
你學的前面才會了解後面的
Then if you search for a piece of content you want to know
那你如果搜尋到一段你要了解的內容
but you haven't heard before
但是你沒有聽過前面
maybe you don't understand
可能你聽不懂
then i don't know the background
那我不知道背景
But I don't know how to find their relevant knowledge
但是我也不知道如何去找他們的相關知識
I don't know what else to look for
也不知道還有什麼可以找
because of this relationship
因為這樣的關係
We just want to do an online course
我們就想做一個網路的課程
But it is intellectually structured
但是它是有知識結構的
This knowledge structure is what we just said
這個知識結構就我們剛才有說到的事情
But we use another thing
但是我們利用另外一件事
Online courses often have auxiliary slides
網路課程常常都是有輔助投影片的
we use auxiliary
我們就用輔助
slideshow to do it
投影片來做這件事
For example
舉例來講
I can join the meeting with a slideshow and its key
我可以以投影片以及它的關鍵與會
to build knowledge structure
來建立知識結構
I put the entire course content
我把整個課程內容
in slides
以投影片為單位
Each slide is cut into a small segment
切成每一張投影片就是一小段
Each subsection is represented by its key
每一小段以它的關鍵與會
as the core of knowledge
作為知識的核心
So I can put these keys in the meeting
於是我可以把這些關鍵與會
Draw a picture to describe the relationship between them
畫成圖來描述他們之間的關係
So each of my clips of slides
於是我每一個投影片的小段
while providing a wealth of knowledge
同時提供豐富的知識
For example, how long is it?
譬如說它的長度是多長
you want to see how long it is
你要看它要多長
Then what are the key participants
然後關鍵與會是哪些
What are the relevant key participants
相關的關鍵與會是哪些
What are the other related slides etc.
其他相關的投影片是哪些等等
This helps users click to browse
這樣子幫助使用者點選瀏覽
If you do a search and find the statement
你如果去做搜尋找到的語句
I also provide snippets of slideshows that belong
我也提供所屬的投影片的小段
and its related information
以及它的相關資訊
to help users click through
來幫助使用者點選瀏覽
for example
举个例子
This is what we show you below
这个就是我们底下给各位看的
this is a class
这是一门课
This class is my class
这门课就是我开的课
digital voice processing
数位语音处理
The content of this course is bilingual in Chinese and English
这门课的内容是中英雙语混杂的
That is to say, my lectures are taught in Chinese
也就是说我上课是用中文讲的
But all the professional numbers in it
但是里面所有的专业数语
It's all in English and not translated into Chinese
都是英文没有翻成中文
So it's a mixture of Chinese and English
所以是中英混杂的
and spontaneous speech
而且是自发性的语音
Which means I didn't read it from the script.
也就是说我并不是照稿念的
I watched the slide show in class
上课就是看了投影片
just wait
就讲了等等
such a signal
这样的讯号
So let's look at such a system
那么我们来看这样的一个系统
We are called NTU Virtual Teachers
我们称为台大虚拟教师
this is his website
这是他的网站
this is on the website
这个是在网站上
So we're now connecting directly through the network
所以我们现在直接透过网路连线
link to that site
连到那个网站去
this is my class
这是我这门课
digital voice processing
就是数位语音处理
So this one was recorded in 2006
那么这个是在2006年所录的
So it was also
所以是当时也是
It was recorded seven years ago
是七年前的录音
This was done in 2009
这个完成是在2009年
So it's four years old
所以也是四年历史了
we just said
我们刚才说
We just divide it according to the slides
我们就是把它根据投影片来分
for example
譬如说
This is the first one
这个是第一张里面的
each
每一张
first slide
第一张投影片
second slide
第二张投影片
etc.
等等
Let's say I order the fourth slide
譬如说我点个第四张投影片
I think this is the fourth slide
我觉得这是第四张投影片
etc.
等等
I can also watch the next slide here
我还可以在这边看下一张投影片
previous slide
上一张投影片
this is fine
这个都可以
He told me a bunch of info here
他告诉我一大堆讯息在这里
For example
举例来讲
this slide
这一张投影片
It took a total of three minutes and 44 seconds to finish the speech
总共花了三分44秒讲完
His position is in the first of eighteen
他的位置在十八张里面的第一张
This slideshow of him in the first one
他在第一张里面的这一张投影片
above wait
上面等等
I can also say for example
我也可以譬如说
come back
说回来
i choose one
我选择一个
For example, the seventh
譬如说第七张
i can watch
我就可以看
For example, in the seventh
譬如说第七张里面的
a certain slide
某一张投影片
for example this
譬如說這個
This is his sixth slide
這個是他的第六張投影片
It's his eighth slide, etc.
就是他第八張投影片等等
Then I can also see that
那我也可以看到說
in my slide
我這個投影片裡面
He said the full length of the slideshow is 2 minutes and 30 seconds
他說這張投影片的全長是2分30秒
He has a 15 second sample
他有一個15秒的摘樣
Then let me listen to this 15 second sample
那我來聽聽看這15秒的摘樣
click down
點下去
i can hear it all
我可以聽全部了
we listen to a 15 second sample of his
我們聽一個他15秒的摘樣
Hope this network can work
希望這個網路可以work
Therefore the higher frequency part
因此越高頻的部分
the fainter the less clear
越微弱越不清楚
then we'll pull it up a bit
那我們就把它拉高一點
So let's compare the sensitive feeling
那麼讓我們的比較sensitive的感覺
can feel it here
能夠在這裡能夠感覺的出來
That's what we're talking about here
那這個就是我們這邊所說的
This preemphasis is a basic statement that it is pulling up
這個preemphasis它在拉高的基本的一個說法
That's the 15 minute pill
这就是那15分钟的摘药
The title of my slide is pre-emphasis
我这一张的投影片的标题就是pre-emphasis
Then take the medicine in 15 seconds
那这15秒摘药
i can listen to all the wait
我可以听全部的等等
Of course I can also search
那当然我也可以去搜寻
We can look here to search
我们可以看看这边可以搜寻
For example, let's say where I am listening to a lecture
譬如说假设说我在哪里听演讲
I also heard someone say that it looks like a Blackbird Algo
也听到有人说好像一个Blackbird Algo
what
什么东西
is it in here
是不是在这里面呢
I'll look for it
我来找找看
so i clicked it in
所以我把它点进去
let me do a search
我来做一个搜寻
it tells me right away
它马上告诉我这里面
The entire course is 45 hours
这整门课程45小时里面
A total of 56 talks about
总共有56次讲到
Blackbird Algo you typed
你输入的Blackbird Algo
But in fact, if you look closely, you will find
但是其实你仔细看一看就发现
Actually what's in it
其实这里面有的是什么
Is Blackbird Algo
是Blackbird Algo
That's it
这个就说明
I'm not actually
其实我不是在
from identified words
根据辩识出来的词
word recognition
辩识出来的字找字
I'm not looking for words
我不是找字
Because I typed Blackbird Algo
因为我输入的是Blackbird Algo
But what I found was Blackbird Algo
但是我找到的其实是Blackbird Algo
But I found it by the sound
但是我是根据声音找的
Because this sound is exactly like this sound
因为这个声音跟这声音确实很像
I'm looking for the sound
我找的确实是声音
He said you gotta find the BlackWare Algox
他说你要找到BlackWare Algox们
A total of 56 occurrences
总共出现56次
Every time it's kind of like Google's page
每一次这有点像Google的页面
For example, this is the first time that this sentence is 8 seconds long
比如说这第一次有这一句长8秒钟
It's in the slideshow on page 12 of Chapter 4
它是在第四章的第12页投影片里面
You can just listen to these 8 seconds
你要只听这8秒也可以
I want to hear the whole of this too
我要听整个的这个也可以
etc.
等等
But if you want to listen for only 8 seconds
但是如果要只听了8秒
probably can't hear anything
大概听不出什么东西来了
Usually we recommend
通常我们会建议
Should be listening to the whole slideshow
应该是听整张投影片
Can I listen to the whole slideshow?
这张整张投影片我能不能听呢
he will tell me
他会告诉我说
What are the key words of this slideshow
这张投影片的关键词是哪些
With BlackWare Algox
有BlackWare Algox
Etc., etc
等等等等
this is his keyword
这是他的关键词
So I can judge based on this
所以我可以根据这个来判断
do i listen to him
我要不要听他
Let's say I choose to say I'm coming to hear
假设我选择说我要来听
I can just click in
我就可以点进去
I should basically get that page
我基本上应该得到那一页
didn't you give it to me
你它没给我吗
I'll try this and see if it works
我来试这个好了 看看这个有没有
It doesn't have it. I'm sorry. I don't know why.
它没有耶 这个真抱歉 不知为什么
let's pick another
我们再来选一个
I think there is something wrong with the network
我觉得是网络有点状况
With that, this is chapter 12
有了 这是第12章
Slideshow
投影片
inside this one
这一张里面
he told me
他就告诉我说
this slide
这一张投影片
if you want to listen
你如果要听的话
there are 22 minutes
有22分钟
he's in the fourth place
他在第四张的位置
position in all
在全部的里面的位置
The position of this one in the fourth one
这一张在第四张里面的位置
it's here
在这里
you can listen to all
你要听全部也可以
You can also listen to gossip
要听杂谣也可以
at the same time is important
同时很重要
he told me
他告诉我
what is his keyword
他的keyword是什么
Other keywords include EM
他关键词包括EM
Include the delta here
包括这里的delta
Including backword, elkism, etc.
包括backword,elkism等等
Here it says
这边说明说
above these are
这上面这些是
Keywords for this slideshow
这一张投影片的关键词
The bottom is with this keyword
底下就是跟这个关键词
Related keywords are below
相关的关键词在底下
This is not only in this page
这个不仅仅在这一页里面
maybe the whole class
可能是整门课里面
Related keywords are below
相关的关键词在底下
so i can go down there
所以我可以走到下面来
for example
譬如说
It should be down here
这边应该要往下一点
Why can't I go down?
怎么走不下来了呢
how do i go down a bit
我这怎么样走到下面一点
Here are the positions where I want to show my keywords
这底下要秀我的关键词的那些位置的
The screen is too small, right?
画面太小了是吧
ok, I have to use the explanation
ok 我只好用说明的了
But actually I have it here
但其实我这边是有的
For example, I know
譬如说我知道了
i can click
我可以点一下
for example
举例来讲说
What I want to see now is this keyword
我现在想要看的是这个关键词
forward algorithm
forward algorithm
I just click
我就点一下
That's right. That's it.
对 这样就有了
it just told me
它就告诉我说
you are looking for this keyword
你要找这个关键词
It first appears in Chapter 4 of the
它第一次出现在第四章的
Chapter 12 Inside the same slice
第十二章同一片里面
Second will appear in these
其次会出现在这些里面
so you need to know what it is
所以你要知道它是什么的话
if you don't know
如果你不知道的话
maybe start listening here
也许先从这里开始听起
then listen to these
然后再听这些
you talk about this now
你现在再讲这些
should know
应该就知道了
So this is the relationship between these keywords
所以这个是这些关键词的关系
We should have drawn keywords into a picture
我們本來說是應該把關鍵詞畫成一張圖的
But then no drawing
不過後來沒有畫圖
Because this picture is too complicated
因為這個圖太複雜了
So which keywords are related to each keyword
所以每個關鍵詞跟哪些關鍵詞相關
We'll just write it right here
我們就直接寫在這裡了
For example, this is the Begger Algor
譬如說這個是Begger Algor
if i click in
我如果點進去的話
I'll tell me
我就會告訴我說
This Begger Algor first appeared here
這個Begger Algor第一次出現在這裡
and then second appear inside these
然後其次出現在這些裡面
I want to listen to the first time should start here
我要聽第一次應該從這裡開始
I can go in from here
我可以從這點進去
then here comes this one
那就到了這一張
I can just go in here and wait
我就可以這進去等等
So I get a knowledge structure of the whole course
因此我得到一個整個課程的知識結構
Make it easier for users to find what you want
讓使用者比較容易去找到你想要的東西
good
好
This is our second display
這是我們的第二個展示
third display
第三個展示
we're talking about language learning
我們要講的是語言學習
What we're showing you is a virtual language tutor
我們給各位看的是一個虛擬的語言家教
What about this we can imagine
這個呢 我們可以想像
Language learning is increasingly important
語言學習是越來越重要的事
Because we are a globalized world
因為我們這是一個全球化的世界
Everyone needs a language other than his mother tongue to help him
每一個人都需要母語以外的語言來幫助他
But when learning a language other than your mother tongue
但是學習母語以外的語言的時候
A bunch of additional teaching is the most effective but expensive
一堆的加教是最有效 但是很貴
So therefore we feel that
那麼因此呢 我們覺得說
You can let the computer take over the role of this pile of tutoring
可以讓電腦來擔任這個一堆的加教
Computers are not as good as humans
電腦雖然不如人啊
But the biggest advantage is
但是呢 最大的好處是
It can be used countless times anytime, anywhere
它可以隨時隨地使用無數次
it doesn't get angry and doesn't rest
它也不會生氣 也不要休息
hard work
可以說是任勞任怨
based on that
那基於這一點呢
Computers can win
電腦可以有贏人的地方
Of course we are not saying that computers are going to replace teachers
那當然我們不是說電腦要去取代老師
is impossible
是不可能的
But a language teacher can use this software
但是一個語言老師可以利用這個軟體
To teach a large group of students many classes at the same time
來同時教一大群學生很多班級
We can also have online schools
我們也可以因此有網路學校
There are social networks for learners, etc.
有學習者的社群網路等等
Okay, so the one I'm showing you is Chinese from National Taiwan University.
好 那麼給各位看的這個是台大華裔
software for learning chinese
學習華語的軟體
teaching foreigners to learn Chinese
教外國人學華語的
what's in there
那裡面呢
The main content is
主要內容是
Various most important communication functions
各種最重要的溝通功能
including greetings
包括問候啊
ask
詢問啊
invite, wait
邀約啊等等
every communication function
每一個溝通功能
we have basic sentences
我們有基本巨型
different application scenarios
跟不同的應用情境
For example, people, facts, places, etc.
譬如說人事實地物等等
Then what
然後呢
It can contain all pronunciation units
它可以包含所有的發音單位
and this change in tone
以及這個聲調的變化
it can contain
它可以包含
Most of the basic common words
絕大多數的基本常用詞
from easy to difficult
由易而難
Then what
然後呢
Consider actual language learning needs
考量實際語言學習需要
then this is
那這個是
Our Chinese teacher at the Liberal Arts College of National Taiwan University
我們的台大的文學院的華語老師
Help us design course content
幫我們設計的課程內容
good
好
what's down there
底下呢
I can show you this National Taiwan University Mandarin
就可以給各位看這個台大華語
This is the Chinese website of National Taiwan University
這是台大華語的網站
There are 12 units in total
總共有12單元
That is, the 12 communication functions are written here
就是12個溝通功能寫在這裡
Let's take an example
我們舉一個例子
Let's look at this praise and response
我們來看這個讚美與回應
how do i order this
是怎样我是要点这个吗
ok
ok
then which one do i order
然后我要点哪一个
this is
这个是
then come back here
那就回到这儿来了
ok good
ok好
This is a compliment response
这是赞美语回应
We have the basic shape and the applied shape
我们这边有基本形有应用形
let's see one
我们来看一个
For example, in the basic form, there are
比如说基本形里面有
e.g. grade response
比如说等级回应
What is graded response?
什么叫等级回应呢
let's take a look
我们看一下
when people praise
人家赞美的时候
Are you accepting compliments?
你是接受赞美呢
Or accept compliments politely?
还是客气的接受赞美呢
Or reluctantly accept compliments?
还是勉强的接受赞美呢
Still don't accept compliments?
还是不接受赞美呢
It will be all right
都可以
This is to teach foreigners how to speak Chinese
这是教老外怎么说华语的
Then what do we mean by politely accepting compliments?
那我们说客气的接受赞美是怎样的
okay what about this time
好这回怎么办
a good student
一個好學生
Thanks
謝謝
you are too polite
你太客氣了
you are such a good student
你真是一個好學生
where where
哪裡哪裡
I am over-flattered
過獎過獎
you are such a good student
你真是一個好學生
Don't dare not dare
不敢當不敢當
Well, this is what he said politely.
好這個是他說的客氣的
Four ways to accept compliments
接受讚美的四種說法
So
那麼
shall i use this book first
我先用這個書嗎
OK
OK
suppose i now
假設我現在
do a single sentence exercise
要做一個單句練習
practice a single sentence
練某一個單句
this music is
這個音樂是
well this is just now
好這個是剛才的
I can choose one of these eight sentences, for example,
這八個句子我可以選一個句子譬如說
you are such a good student
你真是一個好學生
did he go in
他有進去嗎
i didn't open it
我沒打開
ok ok do it again
ok 好 重來一次
ok good
ok 好
Again
再來一次
you are such a good student
你真是一個好學生
what's wrong with this
這個又是怎麼了
He doesn't listen to me today, it's really helpless
他今天都不听我的话 真是没办法
Do you want to plug it in or not? Plug it in, right?
你这个要插还是不要插 插了是吧
Don't plug it in yet, right?
先不要插 是吧
Can't try it, it's already nine o'clock
不能试看看 已经九点了
ok ok let's try again
OK 好 我们再试一次
you are such a good student
你真是一个好学生
No, one more time
不对啊 再来一次
It's not right now
现在不对了
You said the mic was too big, my mic is too big
你說麥克風太大 我的這個麥克風太大
OK
OK
you are such a good student
你真是一個好學生
You said I'm going to turn this off, right?
你說我要把這個關掉是吧
Is this the effect?
是這個影響嗎
in this way
這樣子
OK
OK
good start
好 開始
you are such a good student
你真是一個好學生
right
對
ok this time it's ok
好 這回就好了
Okay, he told me this sentence, the total score of what I just said is here
好 这句话他告诉我说 我刚才讲的话总分在这里
My four scores are here, for example, the pronunciation is 85 points
我四个分数在这里 譬如说这个发音是85分
We can see why it is 85 points
我们可以看一下是为什么85分呢
Then you will immediately discover what I just said, this is the pronunciation of each word
那你马上发现我刚才讲的 这是每一个字的发音的情形
All the coiled snakes I deliberately did not coil
所有的卷蛇我都故意没有卷
So he told me all the curly sounds were wrong
所以他就告诉我这些卷蛇音都错了
These snake sounds are wrong. For example, this body only has 50 points.
这些卷蛇音的错的 譬如说这个身只有50分
then this wait wait wait
那么这个 等等等等
So on average I only have 100 points for everything else
因此平均起来我就只有 别的我都是100分
This is this only 50 points
这个就是这个只有50分
So my pronunciation is a total of 85 points
所以我的发音总共是85分
So what if I don't know how to pronounce this snake sound?
那假设我不会发这个卷蛇音怎么办呢
i can click
我可以点一下
ok listen
OK 听一下
This is the difference in the poses of my four faculties
这是我的四根老师的式的差别
I can also click here
我也可以点在这里上
OK I order this
OK 我点这个
He will tell me how to roll when you roll
他会告诉我说你的卷时候该怎么卷的了
It's going to be rolled like this
是要这样子卷的了
etc.
等等
OK, so this is 85 points
好 那么这个是85分
We see that the pitch is the pitch
我们看这个pitch就是音高
Also how does the tone change
也是声调的变化是怎样
I only have 52 points, what's going on?
我只有52分了 怎么回事
You'll see right away that I pronounced it as a whole on purpose.
你马上发现我刚才故意把这个念成整
Turned into a third tone so he told you this isn't right
变成第三声 所以他告诉你这个是不对的
And then when this becomes the third tone becomes the second tone
然后当这个变成第三声 变成第二声
You're all one so this is wrong too
你整是一个 所以这个也错了
Just these two mistakes, so the result becomes only 52 points
就这两个错 所以结果就变成只有52分了
So what is this timing?
那么这个timing是什么呢
This is the relative relationship between the length of each of my sounds
这是我每一个音的长短相对的关系
How much is it different from the teacher's
比起老師的來差多少
Then what
然後呢
This emphasis is the accent
這個 emphasis 是重音
That is to say
也就是說呢
every sound of me
我每一個音的
the size of the volume
音量的大小
How much is it different from the teacher, etc.
跟老師比起來差多少等等
That's how much my total score is
那總共我的總分是這樣多
good
好
so i can do a conversation exercise now
那我現在可以做一個對話練習
Thanks
謝謝
leave
離開
you are too polite
你太客氣了
thank you for being so kind
谢谢你太客气了
didn't go in
沒進去
I want
我要
This is the third demo
這個是第三個demo
I didn't make it but here we go
我沒成功 不過我們就到這裡
I go back to the last
我回到剛才的最後
We actually did one thing now
我們其實現在做了一件事情
Another thing I'm actually doing right now is a conversation game
我現在其實在做另外一件事情是對話遊戲
Because the one just now looked less fun
因為剛才那個看起來比較沒那麼好玩
So we hope to make a richer dialogue
所以我們希望是做成一個比較豐富的對話
Let people learn like playing games
讓學習的人可以像玩遊戲一樣
Because the game is people love to eat
因為遊戲是人很愛吃
So
那麼
The way we think about it is to put
我們想的辦法就是把
Make a number-like dialogue script
做成一個數狀的對話劇本
then every love
那麼每一個情
Let's assume a situation like dining in a restaurant
我們假設個情境譬如說餐廳用餐
then let this
然後讓這個
Each time there are many sentences to choose from
每一回都有很多句子可以選
Then choose along the way
那麼一路選下去就
different roads get different paths
不同的路 得到不同的路徑
the practice times of pronunciation unit
就得到發音單位的練習次數
all different
都各不相同
So the things a computer can do
因此電腦可以做的事情
It is to replace users online at any time
就是隨時替 線上替使用者
choose the best path
選擇最佳路徑
Wherever you say something bad
凡是哪個地方說不好的話
We'll try to make it as fast as possible
我們就盡量讓它在最短時間內
the most times, let it train well
出現最多次 讓它好好訓練
For example, it doesn't roll its tongue
譬如說它不會捲舌
I just give it a lot of retroflex
我就給它很多捲舌音
Let it roll like hell, wait
讓它拼命去捲去 等等
i can say something different
我可以說不同的話
to practice the same sound
來練習同樣的音
Instead of practicing the same sentence over and over
而不需要反覆練習同一句話
Because we are going to practice repeatedly
因為我們現在是要反覆練
that good student good student
那個好學生好學生
I can now stop repeating
我現在可以不用反覆
I can use different in the dialog
我可以用不同的在對話中
practice repeatedly
反覆練習
Haven't learned the pronunciation unit yet
還沒有學到發音單位
so i can show up early now
所以我現在可以盡早出現
Learn all the pronunciation units well in a short period of time
在對短時間之內把所有的發音單元都學好
For example
舉個例子來講
This is the waiting and ordering part
這是待位及點餐的部分
This one tries to say welcome, etc.
這個試著說歡迎光臨等等
Is there any place?
有沒有位置呢
you can say yes or no
你可以說有還是沒有
what if there is
如果有的話又可以怎樣
If not, how can we wait
沒有的話又可以怎樣等等
So this is a vertical structure
所以這就是一個豎壯的結構
what about us
那麼我們整個呢
has a long dialogue script
有一個很長的對話劇本
Start with a phone call
先從電話邀約開始
Ordering, positioning, asking for directions until waiting for the table to order and serve
訂餐定位問路一直到待位點餐上菜
until the farewell
一直到復帳道別
you can go back
還可以再回過頭去
because after you turn around
因為你回過頭之後
You have to eat the next meal after eating
你吃完還要吃下一餐飯
keep eating with different people
有約不同的人繼續吃飯
Then every road can be different
那麼每一個路可以走不同的話
So if this tongue roll won't roll
所以如果這個卷舌不會卷
Just let it roll down and wait
就給它一直卷下去等等
Ok, that's all for today
好今天說到此為止
One last word
最後說一下
open sesame
芝麻開門
This is an allusion to Alibaba
這是一個阿里巴巴的典故
you guys know what it means to say
各位知道它的意思是在說
just talk
只要開口就說話
The door that can open the treasure
可以開啟寶藏的大門
this is human
這是人
man's dream since time immemorial
人類自古以來的夢想
So what we're going to talk about today is actually
那我們今天要說的事情其實是
The Internet is the single most important treasure trove of knowledge in the future
網路是未來唯一最重要的知識寶藏
And the time to open the door to the treasure of knowledge with sound
而用聲音開啟知識寶藏大門的時間
is getting closer
是越來越接近
Of course many people will ask
當然很多人會問說
You use a machine to recognize life
你用機器辨識人生
So what
So what
At best it is the same as the human ear
充其量它跟人耳一樣
In fact, you still have so many mistakes today
其實你今天還有那麼多錯
Can't compare with human ear
還不能跟人耳比
But it does not matter
但是沒關係
Because machines can process huge amounts of information
因為機器可以處理巨量資訊
But the machine can repeat
但是機器可以反覆
Repeat service anytime, anywhere
隨時隨地反覆服務
These two points are the machine native human
這兩點是機器原生人類的
so what we have to do
所以我們要做的事情
is how to take advantage of these strengths of the machine
就是如何利用機器的這些長處
Well though it has a place
那麼它雖然有一個地方
not so good
不怎麼好
Should be pretty good too
應該也是很不錯的
ok i want to end my speech today
好我想今天演講到這裡
thank you
謝謝各位
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you, Mr. Li, for your wonderful speech.
好 謝謝這個李老師的精采的演講
Although we have two full hours
雖然我們滿兩個鐘頭
Let's discuss Q&A in about 10 minutes
我們可以研討一下子在10分鐘左右的Q&A吧
Do you have any questions?
那大家有沒有什麼問題
please
來請
Teacher, is this part of AI?
老師你這也算是AI的一部分嗎
You can ask the microphone
你那個可以問麥克風
OK
OK
This is part of AI
這也算是AI的一部分
does it count
是不是算
Does it count as part of the AI?
算不算AI的部分
It actually depends on how AI people define AI
那其實要看AI的人怎麼把AI界定
sure
當然可以
But some people define the AI ​​key very
但是也有的人把AI鍵界定得非常的
Narrow's words
Narrow的話
Maybe he said it doesn't count
也許他說這個不算
I think this is fine
那我覺得這個都可以
Depends on see
Depends on看
That should make it very clear what I'm talking about here.
那應該講很清楚我這邊講的是什麼事情
is the signal with this voice
是用這個聲音的訊號
Then I use a lot of math and a lot of programming
然後我用很多的數學跟很多的程式
find a way to do it
想辦法來做
All the things audio signals can do
所有聲音訊號可以做的事
Then it is very clear that the definition is like this
那這是很清楚的定義是這樣
Then the AI ​​person wants to say whether he is AI or not
那麼AI的人要說他是AI還是不是AI
I think it's all right
我想是都可以
OK
OK
good
好
please teach me
請教一下
that today's report was wonderful
那個今天的報告很精彩
Thanks
謝謝
There is still an application to the theory of this congressman's identification
對於這個議員辯識的這個理論還有應用
But the current MPs recognize
但是現在的議員辯識
As if this is still not so tomorrow
好像這個還是不是那麼明天
what is the most important bottleneck
那最重要的瓶頸是什麼
For example, you say that sesame seeds open the door
比如例子你說芝麻開門
But the flower sound of the sesame opening door is not accurate
但是這個芝麻開門的花音不準確
Many flower sounds are inaccurate
很多的花音是不準確的
it won't open the door
它就不開門
Does this technically include software?
那這個技術上是不是包括軟體
Is it possible to solve this problem already?
是不是已經對這個方面可以解決
Can make it more general and friendly
可以讓它可以更普遍更Friendly
Or are you suggesting that everyone go to the cloud for coordination?
或者你是建議大家都要上雲協調
Otherwise, there is no way for this congressman to identify
不然的話這個議員辯識就沒有辦法做
Thanks
謝謝
i want to make a point first
我想要先說明一點
It's just that you found out that something doesn't work
就是剛才你發現有些不工作
It's not that my pronunciation is bad
不是因為這個我的發音有什麼不好
but a matter of contact
而是一些接觸的問題
Or the problem that the signal is not coming in
或者訊號沒進去的問題
It's just that he can't recognize it himself
就是他本身不能辨識
the same
同樣呢
This is about different accents for different people
這個關於不同人不同的口音這一點
all these decades
所有這個幾十年來
Many people have done various researches
已經非常多人做各種各樣的研究
there are many ways to handle this
那有很多方法來處理這件事
Then you can also understand today
那你也可以了解今天
There are indeed some systems that do a good job
確實有一些系統做得不錯
For example, there are some good features on mobile phones
譬如說手機上也有一些很好的功能
Then he is indeed working with different people
那他確實不同人在用都 work
That means that in fact this
那表示說其實這種
adapt to different
適應不同的
of different voices
遇者的不同的聲音的
different accent thing
不同的口音這件事
In fact, there are already quite good solutions
其實已經有相當好的 solution
That's got pretty good results.
那都得到相當好的結果了
only limited time today
只是今天限於時間
I can't have this
我沒有辦法已經這個
too much time
超過太多時間了
no way to talk
沒有辦法多講
There are so many ideas to do this
那有非常多的想法來做這件事情
There are many effective ways
有非常多有效的方法
Allows different accents to be handled
讓不同的口音都能夠處理
So many systems today
那今天非常多的系統
You can see that they are all speaker independent
你可以看到他們都是 speaker independent
He can listen to what different people are saying
那麼不同的人在說他都可以聽的
This should not be the main obstacle
這應該不是最主要的障礙所在
But the main obstacle should be to say
但是最主要障礙應該是說
Speech recognition will never be 100% correct
語音辨識永遠不會100%是正確
always have a lot of mistakes
永遠有很多錯
We must live with those mistakes
我們必須live with那些錯誤
All the applications I just talked about
我剛才講的所有的應用
In fact, they are all live with those mistakes
其實都是live with那些錯誤的
For example
舉例來講
when i do a summary
當我做一個摘要的時候
I obviously let there be a typo in it, it doesn't matter
我明明讓裡面有錯字沒有關係
Because as long as I get enough of it right
因為只要我辨識正確的夠多
i know what their point is
我知道他們重點是什麼
I'll just grab it
我就抓出來就好了
it's okay to be wrong
那些錯的沒關係
I'm looking for the same thing
我要找哪個東西也是一樣
if i'm looking for this
我要找這個的話
That is, I can't be right about everything.
也就是我不可能全部都對
But as long as I catch his stuff
但是只要我抓到他的東西就行了
So all of our applications today are in this category
那麼我們今天所有都是這一類的應用
Like if you have some product on your phone
就好像你如果在手機上有一些產品
it can answer your questions
它可以回答你什麼問題
also the same
也是一樣
It is actually able to identify the inside
它其實就是能夠辨識裡面
important key to your important problem
你重要的問題的重要的關鍵
it caught
它抓到了
It just knows how to answer
它知道怎麼回答就行了
Basically we all think in this direction
那基本上我們都朝這個方向來想
The real state today should be what I just said
那今天真正的狀態應該是我剛才講的
We can't be 100% right
我們並不能做到100%都是正確
The situation will be different if the judgment is different
那比判當不同的狀況就會不一樣
if you talk on the street
你如果在街上講話
This one has a lot of background noise
這個有很多背景雜訊
If I'm chatting with someone else
我如果因為在跟別人聊天
So what this says
所以這個說的話
It's not the same as the usual pronunciation, etc.
跟平常的發音方不太一樣等等
will change
都會改變的
That's why my error always happens
那因此我的錯誤永遠會發生
This may be the biggest problem right now
這個可能是現在最大的難題
good
好
yes
是
you have to click
你要按一下
Excuse me Mr. Li
請問李老師
then in the western language
那麼在西方的那個語言
They are phonetic characters
他們是拼音文字
Are there fewer obstacles in this regard?
是不是這一方面的障礙就比較少
if it is like this
如果是這樣的話
If we can make Chinese also
如果我們能夠把中文也
Pinyin as much as possible
盡量拼音化的話
Can this obstacle be broken?
是不是這個障礙就可以破除
Although some of this is pinyin
這個雖然有的是拼音文字
some are some this block
有的是有的是這個方塊
But judging by the sound signal
但是從聲音訊號來看
they look alike
他們是長得很像的
pretty much the same thing
差不多是同樣的東西
It's just that when I render with text
只是當我用文字來呈現的時候
What kind of text is used to present
是用哪一種文字來呈現
Then of course when this text appears
那當然這個文字呈現的時候
its structure is different
它的結構是不一樣的
from this point of view
從這個觀點來講
We feel that doing Chinese is the same as doing English
我們覺得其實做中文跟做英文
almost the same difficulty
幾乎難度是一樣
Then each has its own difficulties
那麼各有各的困難
Chinese has a lot of difficulties
中文有一堆困難
just said
剛才說過了
English also has a lot of difficulties
英文也有一堆困難
Today's Possible English Recognition
今天可能英文的辨識
better effect
效果比較好
That's because many people do it
那是因為做的人多
Then make great efforts
然後下的功夫大
The data they collect is much
他們收集的這個data多
they use more
他們用更大量的
say thousands of hours
譬如說幾千小時
Tens of thousands of hours of data
幾萬小時data
Thousands of computers connected to run
幾千台電腦連線去跑
then they can do better
那他們可以做得比較好
In fact, we feel
那其實我們感覺
The real difficulty is close
真正難度是接近的
Then all the problems are also close
那所有的問題也是接近的
just different
只是不一樣
In fact, Chinese is also spelled out with a bunch of sounds.
其實中文也一樣是一堆音拼出來的
not much different from English
跟英文沒什麽太大的不同
If we look at it from the level of sound
我們如果從音的層次來看的話
The difference lies in the presentation of the text
他們不同在於文字的呈現不一樣
Of course, the text rendering is different and has a great impact
當然文字呈現不一樣影響很大
Because I'm going to use those words to help me train
因為我要用那些文字來幫助我訓練
So why?
那麽因此呢
For example, speaking Chinese because it is a square character
譬如說中文因為是方塊字
So when I use text to render
所以我用文字來呈現的時候
For example, a lot of words have the same pronunciation
譬如一大堆字都同音
So what are these issues that are different
那麽是什麽這些問題是有不同的地方
So if the computer's CPU speeds up
所以如果電腦的CPU再加快
will it be better
是不是會好一點
all of course
當然就是所有的
Today's speech technology has not reached any stage
我們今天的語音技術已經進不到哪個階段
You can buy pretty good voice systems on the street
各位在街上可以買得到相當不錯的語音系統
Do it all on your phone
在你的手機上都做到了
how do those
那些怎麽做的
it uses a very large amount
它用非常大量的
Mobile phone has a lot of data
手機非常大量的data
And a very large amount of calculations to train it and so on
又非常大量的計算去訓練它等等
Of course you're not pretending over there
那當然你不是裝在那邊
Those are not all things installed in the phone
那些不是所有東西裝在手機裡面
The answer to your question is in the cloud
回答你的問題是在雲端
that is to say
那也就是說
Today's Today's Today's Cloud Technology
今天的今天的今天的雲技術
can't get to this stage
進不到這個階段
not the same as 20 years ago
跟20年前不一樣
Of course technology has improved a lot
當然技術進步很多
It is also important because
也有很重要一點是因為
This computer is much faster
這個電腦快了很多
a lot more data
data多了很多
People put in a lot more effort
人家下的功夫多了很多
these things add up
這些東西加起來
Of course there are new technologies
當然有新的技術
All of these have effects
這些全部都有效果都有影響的
Thanks
謝謝
two thousand
兩千
Hello Mr. Li
李老師你好
You spoke very well today
你今天講得很好啊
I want to say that there is a commercial problem.
我想說有一個商業化的問題啊
It is about after the model is built
就是有關於這個model建起來以後
Then this Chinese is actually Chinese
那這個華文其實中國人
A high percentage of the world
在世界的比例很高
If htc these are combined with this
如果htc這些跟這個結合啊
There is a part about intelligent property
就是有關於intelligent property的部分
put it some
把它有些
Because many models
因為很多的model
not a system
不是一個system
If becomes a structure
如果變成一個架構
Then talk to the phone for advice
然後跟手機的建議
Combined with this, it looks like Samsung has mobile phones that use Chinese.
結合那這個起來可以像三星都有手機用華文的部分
he stands here
他站到這一塊
In fact, we can do a market share. Do you have the idea to share all these
其實可以做一個market share有沒有這種想法去把這些全部的
no number i know
no號我知道
The foreign series are also developing well
國外的series他們也發展不錯
Some of the rooms in Taiwan are for tourism
那臺灣的房間有些做旅遊的
It does a good job on mobile as well. Some wins
在手機上也做得不錯有些勝出地方
Is there anything in this plan because National Taiwan University is quite ahead?
這個規劃上面有沒有因為臺大也算是蠻領先的
Make this market a share to balance in the mobile phone
把這個市場做個share去balance在手機的
Competitors above are able to cut a piece out here is one of mine
競爭略士上面能夠切一塊出來這是我的一個
I don't know what to think, no one will go this way
想法不曉得沒有人往這邊再走
Taiwan University doesn't have the same idea, thank you
臺大也沒這個想法謝謝
i think it's a good idea
我想這是很好的想法
But someone needs to do these things
不過呢得要有人來做這些事
Our technology at Taiwan University is very advanced, but
那臺大我們的技術是非常領先的但是
I can't do so many things by myself
只有我一個人是沒辦法做這麼多事的
What I can do is to lead students to make friends with customers and do our research well.
我能做事大概就是帶學生好好的把客交好把我們的研究做好
I'm already passed out from this so I'm unlikely to bother with anything else.
這個我已經累昏掉了所以不太可能再來管別的事
what about the same
那同樣的呢
Certainly a very large market
當然是一個非常大的市場
Then you also understand
那各位也瞭解
For example
那舉例來講
Voice teams around the world today
今天全世界的做語音的團隊
all in Chinese
都做華文
It is not only our Chinese-speaking world
並不是只有我們華語世界
only do Chinese
才做華文而已
This one in North America, this one in Western Europe
這個北美的西歐的這個
including east asia
包括東亞的什麼
Everyone speaks Chinese
大家都做華文
you may know
那各位可能知道
Department of Defense of the United States
美國的國防部
they invested a lot of money
他們投了非常大的錢
Buy thousands of computers for others
給人家買千千萬萬的電腦
Do a very good voice system
做非常好的語音系統
it has two specified languages
它有兩個指定的語言
the first is arabic
第一個是阿拉伯文
The second is Chinese
第二個是中文
This is a global program of the U.S. Department of Defense
這是美國國防部的全球性的計畫
you know why very clearly
你知道為什麼很清楚
US Department of Defense looks
美國國防部看起來
its two enemies
它兩大敵國
the first is arabic
第一個是阿拉伯
The second is the person who speaks Chinese
第二個就是說中文的人
so do chinese
所以做中文
In fact, it is very common today
其實今天已經是非常普遍
then really have the most resources
那麼真正有最多資源
Can do the best Chinese
可以做最好的中文的
That's actually a lot of teams around the world
那其實是全世界很多團隊
Then we in Taiwan can
那我們臺灣今天能夠
the Chinese part
做的中文的部分
we are technically
我們在技術上
Conceptually
在觀念上
Definitely leading
鐵定是領先的
but our resources
但是我們的資源
what can be done
跟能夠做的事情
is now relatively limited
現在是比較有限的
of course
那當然
If there is an industry
如果有產業界
want to do something
想好好做一些事情
I think there is a chance
我覺得是有機會的
Someone needs to think about this
那這個需要有人來想
Someone come to organize
有人來organize
At this stage, it should be said that there is no
現階段應該說沒有
sorry about that
那這個抱歉
this may disappoint you
這個可能讓您失望
that last question
那最後一個問題
I am Zhu Hongyan from the Institute of Modern History
我是近代史所朱鴻延
Just mentioned the American text
剛才提到了美國的文
I didn't want to mention it
本來沒有要提的
But it's basically Sanmou Huntington
不過基本上是三謀Huntington
His Crash of Civilizations
他的Crash of Civilizations
It basically assumes that these two
裡面基本上假設就是這兩種
Democracy has the biggest impact on America
民主對於美國的影響最大
Crash may have generated
Crash可能產生了
He originally predicted that China
他原來預測中國
later became the number one in the Arab world
後來變成阿拉伯世界第一
He actually wanted the order reversed.
他其實原來順序是想反的
Then the question I want to ask is not this
那我要問的問題不是這個
I feel very close
我覺得非常親配
because it's very hard
因為這非常難
very difficult
非常難
so if it was me
所以如果是我
i really can't do it
我真的做不出來
Then what I'm thinking is the other side
那我在想的是另外一方面
is what you just mentioned
就是您剛才提到
is literal language
就是文字語言
seems to be text lead
似乎是文字帶頭
language is built on words
語言是架在文字上
and then to operate
然後來操作
if it is like this
如果是這樣的話
How to communicate with the whole system of book classification
怎麼樣跟圖書分類的整個系統
all the key is
所有的關鍵是
Will it be faster to combine with book classification
跟圖書分類結合會不會比較快
Thanks
謝謝
we didn't think about it
我們倒沒想過這件事
for us
對我們而言
language is language
語言就是語言
languages ​​come in different forms
語言有不同的形式
then the sound is
那麼聲音是
We are called spoken language
我們叫做spoken language
is spoken language
是說出來的語言
The text is written language
文字是written language
is written language
是寫出來的語言
Then if it prints out
然後如果印出來的是
princess language
princess language
printed language
印出來的語言
of course
那當然
Operation still needs to be done through text
操作上還是要透過文字
Then your operation must be through the text
那在您的操作都要透過文字
Text is the basis of language
文字還是語言的基礎
in today's case
在今天來講是這樣
because we have to use these words
因為我們必須用這些文字
or its phonetic symbols to mark these sounds
或者它的音標來標這些聲音
know what it is
知道它是什麼
what is it
它是什麼
but the other way around
但是反過來講
we can also imagine
我們也可以想像
Actually this has some
其實這個有一些
many languages ​​in the world
世界上很多語言
it has no text at all
它根本沒有文字
It can also exist directly
它也可以直接存在
Or rather it has only very simple
或者說它只有非常簡單的
some first blood symbols
一些首血的符號
its language exists
它的語言一樣存在
So from that point of view
所以從那個角度來講
Sound may be something that appeared earlier than words
聲音也許是比文字更早出現的東西
Said the operation is not working
說操作不行
sound does not work
聲音不能操作
or through text
還是要透過文字才能
It seems that our current experience is indeed the case
那似乎我們現在經驗確實是這樣
That is to say, your voice must
就是說你聲音一定要
label it to some extent
某種程度的標它
Then I was able to do many things
然後我才能夠做很多事情
So that target can be text
所以那個標的東西可以是文字
can be phonetic
可以是音標
can be e.g. letters
可以是譬如說字母
different situations have different situations
那不同的情形有不同的狀況
Then in our Chinese we speak square characters
那在我們中文我們講有方塊字
Western languages ​​have pinyin characters, which is the method of marking, etc.
西方語言有拼音文字就是這個標的方法等等
so it's a complicated thing
所以是滿複雜的一件事
Different language situations are different
不同語言狀況是不一樣的
So actually in the field of phonetics
所以其實在語音學界
Almost every language we have has its own
我們幾乎每一種語言都有它自己的
A whole bunch of teams working on their languages
一個一大堆的團隊在做他們的語言
This is to do a good job of language today, at least eighty or ninety
這個是今天好好做語言至少是八九十個以上
You are also kissing me teacher ask for advice
你也kissing me老師請教一下
can i ask a question
可以請教一個問題嗎
That is to say, we are currently saying
就是說我們目前就是說
Let's say we're talking on the phone
比如說我們對著手機講話
it can show text
它能夠顯現出文字來
Will the field improve in the future?
那以後是不是領域會進步到
We use human voice to speak to our mobile phones
我們用人聲語音對著我們手機講
The mobile phone can also answer us with voice
那手機它也可以用聲音回答我們
Thanks
謝謝
this is of course possible
這個當然可以
There should be some systems that do these things now
這個現在應該也有一些系統做到這些事的
because basically
因為基本上來講
It's easier for machines to talk
機器說話是比較容易的事
because it only needs to say one sentence
因為它只要說出一句話
Just let others understand
來別人聽得懂就行了
But you have to identify what this sentence is
但是你要辨識這句話是什麼
is much harder
是難得多
Because that sentence can say thousands of ways
因為那句話可以說的樣子是千千萬萬的
So in fact, we actually have a lot of
那麼因此其實我們今天其實有很多的
e.g. dialogue system
譬如說對話系統
It's all machines talking to people
那都是機器在跟人說話
Even in the country, there are actually many
即使在國內其實也有不少
You may not have noticed
各位也許沒有注意到
Sometimes, for example, the bank makes a phone call to say
有的時候譬如說是銀行打個電話來說
what about your credit card
你的什麼信用卡該怎樣的
or something
或者什麼
Or what the election caller said
或者是選舉的打來電話說什麼
what happened to which candidate
哪個候選人怎樣了
He also said a few words to you
他還跟你講了幾句話
you thought he was real
你還以為他是真的
Actually he is a machine
其實他是機器
This actually exists
這個其實也是有的
that sort of thing exists
那這類事情是存在的
That is to say, will it progress to the point of generalization in the future?
就是說以後會不會進步到就普遍化
Universalization should not be a technical issue
普遍化應該不是技術的問題
It's about having someone with the power of this business
而是要有人有這個business的力量
to drive him
去drive他
Let him really have enough people to do these things
讓他真的有夠多人做這些事情
that should be a chance
那應該就是有機會的
Well, that's because of time
好 那因為時間的關係
We thank you all for your participation
我們謝謝大家的參與
Thank you Professor Li Ningshan for your wonderful speech
謝謝李寧珊教授的精彩演講
Thanks
謝謝
ok thank you thank you
好 謝謝 謝謝